<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The primitive rule of Reformation according to the first liturgy of K. Edward VI, 1549 containing an extract of the same, so far as it is Popishly affected : together with several honourable testimonials thereof from church and state, of that, and of succeeding ages : as also the wishes of several churches and chuchmen of the Reformation, for restoring the said liturgy in parts.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55876</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12202317</idno>
  <idno type="VID">56117</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240970105</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3472</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12279</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12202317</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55876)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56117)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 615:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The primitive rule of Reformation according to the first liturgy of K. Edward VI, 1549 containing an extract of the same, so far as it is Popishly affected : together with several honourable testimonials thereof from church and state, of that, and of succeeding ages : as also the wishes of several churches and chuchmen of the Reformation, for restoring the said liturgy in parts.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Mary Thompson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England --  Liturgy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56117:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56117:1"/>
            <p>THE Primitive Rule OF REFORMATION According to the First Liturgy OF K. EDWARD VI. 1549.</p>
            <p>Containing an EXTRACT of the Same, So far as it is <hi>Popishly Affected,</hi> TOGETHER With several Honourable Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nials thereof from CHURCH and STATE, of that, and of Succeeding AGES.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO, The WISHES of several <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Churchmen</hi> of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> for Resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the said <hi>Liturgy</hi> in PARTS.</p>
            <q>—Antiquam exquirite Matrem, <bibl>
                  <hi>Virg. Aeneid.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>With Allowance</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Mary Thompson</hi> at the Entrance into <hi>Old-Spring-Garden</hi> near <hi>Charing-Cross.</hi> Anno Dom. 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:56117:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56117:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>BEhold the Spirit of the <hi>First Reformers</hi> in the <hi>First Liturgy,</hi> and compare it with the <hi>later Liturgies</hi> of <hi>Succeeding Reformers,</hi> and consider how much <hi>our Reformers</hi> have varied from <hi>Themselves</hi> at <hi>Home!</hi> Next, reflect upon <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Censure of the same; that there were in it <hi>Tolerabiles quaedam Ineptiae,</hi> some Passable Fooleries; and compare it with the Sense that <hi>King,</hi> and both the <hi>Parliament</hi> that <hi>Enforced,</hi> and that which <hi>Repealed</hi> it had of it, as well as Archbishop <hi>Bancroft</hi> and Mr. <hi>Fox;</hi> and see how much <hi>our First Reformers</hi> at <hi>Home</hi> have varied from <hi>Those Abroad!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>First Reformers</hi> indeed acted by no <hi>Spirit</hi> but the <hi>Holy Ghost;</hi> what shall we say of that Spirit by which <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> acted, when he treated the Dictates of the Holy Spirit with so little Reverence, as to Style them, <hi>Tolerable Foole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries?</hi> And if in the Opinion of K. <hi>Edward</hi>'s <hi>Parliament,</hi> the Compilers of the <hi>First Liturgy</hi> might lay claim to, <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum est Spiritui Sancto &amp; Nobis; It seem'd good to the Holy Ghost and to Us:</hi> How came the <hi>Parliament</hi> that <hi>Repealed</hi> it, to be <hi>above</hi> the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> and to assume to themselves a Power to controul and alter his <hi>Decrees,</hi> in Repealing what themselves confess'd, was according to <hi>Gods Word,</hi> and the <hi>Usages</hi> of the <hi>Primitive Church?</hi> To be short, if the <hi>Spirit</hi> which guided the Compilers ef the <hi>First Liturgy</hi> was own'd no less than <hi>Infallible;</hi> how came it to give way to that <hi>Fallible Spirit,</hi> which has appear'd in all the Changes that have past from the <hi>Succeeding Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies</hi> down to the <hi>Present?</hi> For since the Church of <hi>England</hi> has pass'd all along under the Name and Notion of a <hi>Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Law Establish'd,</hi> the <hi>Rules</hi> of <hi>Reformation</hi> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
<pb facs="tcp:56117:3"/> varied in proportion to the Fancy and Humour of the several respective <hi>Reformers</hi> in Place and Power under each <hi>Prince;</hi> Nor have there been fewer <hi>Churches by Law Establish'd,</hi> than <hi>Turns</hi> of <hi>State: New Liturgies</hi> and <hi>New Bibles</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming thus the <hi>Regalia</hi> of every <hi>New King</hi> in Succession; and their <hi>Reigns</hi> distinguished as much by these, as by <hi>New Coines</hi> and <hi>Statutes:</hi> The <hi>Face</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> having suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as many Changes as that of the <hi>Civil Government;</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somuch, as the same Question may be admitted upon a just Comparison of the <hi>late</hi> and <hi>present Liturgies</hi> with the <hi>First,</hi> which was started of <hi>Theseus Ship,</hi> that was <hi>mended</hi> so often, as it became a Problem to all the Wits of <hi>Greece,</hi> whether it was the <hi>Same,</hi> since none of the <hi>Primitive Planks</hi> remain'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Religion</hi> being left at this Ʋncertainty, men have wrote in the dark about <hi>Popery</hi> and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowing either what <hi>Popery</hi> was, or what the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that being called <hi>Popery</hi> in the <hi>later Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> which was not in the <hi>First;</hi> and that made the Church of <hi>England</hi> by <hi>Modern Reformers,</hi> which knew no such Name in the <hi>Beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To clear these Points, is the Design of the following Papers, that is, of the Extract of K. <hi>Edwards</hi> first <hi>Liturgy,</hi> and of the <hi>Testimonials</hi> annexed to it, in the nature of a <hi>Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing</hi> shall I say, or rather of <hi>Hallowing</hi> it, for they want but a little of raising it to as <hi>Sacred a</hi> Character as that of <hi>Episcopacy</hi> it self, and of maintaining that <hi>Liturgy</hi> to be as much <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> as the <hi>Bishops</hi> that were the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Communion</hi> in the <hi>Rubrick</hi> before the <hi>Office,</hi> is Styled the <hi>Mass,</hi> and how well the Name agrees to it, may be gathered from the following Instances. The <hi>Priest</hi> is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to stand in the <hi>Middle</hi> of the <hi>Altar,</hi> with his <hi>Back</hi> towards the <hi>People;</hi> the <hi>Vestments</hi> prescribed the <hi>Priest</hi> are an <hi>Albe</hi> and <hi>Tunicles</hi> with a <hi>Cope:</hi> Besides which, there is mention made of the <hi>Paten</hi> and the <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral,
<pb facs="tcp:56117:3"/> Utensils</hi> and <hi>Ornaments,</hi> now much better known to those that assist at <hi>Mass,</hi> than those that go to <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer.</hi> There is at the time of the <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> an express <hi>Commemoration</hi> of the <hi>Dead,</hi> even as the <hi>Mass</hi> which it Copies in this particular, is declared to be a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for the <hi>Living</hi> and the <hi>Dead.</hi> Nor do the Compilers content themselves with this, but back this with an <hi>Invocation</hi> of <hi>Angels.</hi> And that the <hi>Priest</hi> and <hi>Prayers</hi> may not be in the <hi>Popish Garb</hi> alone, the very <hi>Consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Elements</hi> appear in the <hi>Popish Shapes,</hi> of a <hi>Wafer-Cake</hi> and a <hi>Mingled Chalice.</hi> And what is more yet, they are <hi>Consecrated</hi> by <hi>Crossing</hi> them, much after the manner of the Beginning of the <hi>Canon</hi> of the <hi>Mass,</hi> at the words, <hi>Haec Dona, haec Munera,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>Communicants</hi> are ordered to receive the same at the <hi>Priest's Hand</hi> in their <hi>Mouths,</hi> with such a <hi>Form</hi> of Words, as are but the <hi>English</hi> of those, with which all are <hi>Communicated</hi> at <hi>Mass</hi> at this day; without the Additional Supply of, <hi>Take this in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance,</hi> &amp;c. to give it the contrary Turn of a bare <hi>Commemoration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether the <hi>other Offices,</hi> are not as fair Copies of the <hi>Breviary,</hi> as this of the <hi>Communion</hi> is of the <hi>Mass,</hi> may better appear from consulting the <hi>Extract</hi> it self where the <hi>Reader</hi> in the <hi>Office</hi> of <hi>Baptism,</hi> will meet with <hi>Prayers</hi> appointed for the Shifting of the <hi>Water</hi> in the <hi>Font,</hi> which are a kind of <hi>Exorcisms</hi> for <hi>Dispossessing</hi> of the <hi>Water,</hi> in lieu of the <hi>Antient Exorcisms</hi> for <hi>Dipossessing</hi> of the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</hi> Nor do they stay here, but add the <hi>Anointing</hi> of the Person Baptiz'd, the <hi>Chrysome,</hi> and the <hi>Crossing</hi> of him more fully in the <hi>Popish</hi> Mode, on the <hi>Forehead</hi> and the <hi>Breast</hi> together.</p>
            <p>They also add the <hi>Cross</hi> in <hi>Confirmation,</hi> and in <hi>Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony:</hi> In which <hi>Office,</hi> as also in that of <hi>Visitation</hi> of the <hi>Sick;</hi> the <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Story of <hi>Tobias</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Raguel</hi> is brought into a <hi>Prayer,</hi> though the <hi>Benedicite</hi> and the <hi>Apocryphal Lessons</hi> struggled hard to
<pb facs="tcp:56117:4"/> keep their Places in the <hi>last Liturgy,</hi> after the <hi>late Kings Restoration.</hi> In the <hi>Office</hi> of the <hi>Visitation</hi> of the <hi>Sick,</hi> they go as high as <hi>Extreme Unction,</hi> notwithstanding the shy Insinuation of <hi>later Reformers,</hi> that this was exercised in the Nature of a <hi>Miraculous Gift,</hi> and so determin'd with the <hi>Age</hi> of <hi>Miracles.</hi> Nay, what is more surprizing, they have rais'd it to the Dignity of a <hi>Sacrament</hi> in their <hi>Prayer</hi> upon <hi>Administring</hi> the <hi>Oyles,</hi> as far as an <hi>Outward Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible Sign,</hi> and an <hi>Inward Invisible Grace,</hi> will carry it for a <hi>Sacrament.</hi> Nor are we to forget the grave Comfort and Allowance, which the <hi>Priest</hi> is to give such of the <hi>Sick,</hi> as <hi>would,</hi> but <hi>cannot Communicate;</hi> that upon exercising an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> upon the Merits of <hi>CHRISTS Cross</hi> and <hi>Passion,</hi> such have all the Right to and Advantages of a <hi>Spiritual Communion.</hi> A Term which is yet no Stranger to such * Churches as open their Doors to all such as <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate</hi> in <hi>Intention</hi> and <hi>Desire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concil Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Sess. <hi>22.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> though they stand not so fair for <hi>Communicating actually.</hi> But is chiefly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred here for the sake of such as shut all <hi>Spiritual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants</hi> at once out of their <hi>Churches,</hi> leaving no Place in <hi>Sacrament-time</hi> for any, but the <hi>Actual Communicants:</hi> Although they provide them no better Entertainment, than that of a bare <hi>Spiritual Communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lastly,</hi> To instance in no more; in the <hi>Office</hi> of <hi>Burial</hi> of the <hi>Dead,</hi> besides direct <hi>Prayers</hi> for the <hi>Dead,</hi> such was their <hi>Extraordinary Charity,</hi> as they furnished out over and above, an <hi>Office</hi> of set purpose, of <hi>Communion</hi> for the <hi>Dead.</hi> Now if we speak the Language of that <hi>Liturgy,</hi> as well as of the <hi>Statute</hi> that enforc'd it, of K. <hi>Edward</hi>'s <hi>Injunctions Injunct. 21. Communions</hi> are no more than <hi>Masses:</hi> And if so, we have gain'd this point; that <hi>Masses</hi> for the <hi>Dead,</hi> as Scandalous as they sound in the Ears of <hi>late Reformers,</hi> were not only more Innocent, but highly approv'd of and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd by the <hi>First Reformers.</hi> Nor did they oblige others, to more than they practised themselves, if <hi>Stow</hi> says true, who tells us, <hi>That on</hi> June <hi>19. (1547.) a</hi> Dirge <hi>was Sung
<pb facs="tcp:56117:4"/> in every</hi> Parish Church <hi>in</hi> London,<note place="margin">K. <hi>Henry</hi> II</note>
               <hi>for the</hi> French <hi>King late Deceased</hi> (viz. March <hi>22. last past) Also the Church of S.</hi> Paul <hi>being hanged with</hi> Black, <hi>and a Sumptuous</hi> Herse <hi>set up in the</hi> Choire, <hi>a</hi> Dirge <hi>was there Sung, and on the next Morrow, the Archbishop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted of</hi> Eight Bishops, <hi>all in Rich</hi> Miters, <hi>and other their</hi> Pontificlas, <hi>did Sing a</hi> Mass <hi>of</hi> Requiem. Thus <hi>Stow</hi> in his <hi>Chronicle,</hi> in the Life of <hi>Edward VI.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ʋpon the whole matter it appears, that such Doctrines and Practices as now pass for <hi>Popish,</hi> were in the Beginning of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> esteem'd no other than the genuine Doctrines and Practices of the Church of <hi>England, by Law Established.</hi> As for Instance, that of <hi>Communion in One Kind,</hi> at least in some Cases of Necessity; for so much appears from the Statute of <hi>1 Edw. VI.</hi> Requiring that <hi>Sacraments</hi> be commonly <hi>Administred</hi> in Both Kinds, if Necessity <hi>does not require</hi> otherwise: By which it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that they took it for no <hi>Precept</hi> to Communicate in <hi>Both Kinds,</hi> for no <hi>Necessity</hi> can lye to break a flat <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept.</hi> Nor does it less appear, from the <hi>Rubrick</hi> in the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> which says, notwithstanding the <hi>Division</hi> of the <hi>Wafer-Cake,</hi> men are not to take it, that <hi>CHRIST</hi> is <hi>more</hi> in the <hi>whole,</hi> and <hi>less</hi> in the <hi>less.</hi> For if <hi>CHRIST</hi> be <hi>whole</hi> in every <hi>Particle</hi> of the <hi>Host,</hi> certainly he is <hi>whole</hi> in the <hi>whole Host;</hi> and by consequence, if he be <hi>whole</hi> in <hi>each kind, Communion</hi> in <hi>One Kind</hi> cannot be called truly <hi>Half</hi> a <hi>Sacrament:</hi> To this we may add, that of <hi>Invocation</hi> of <hi>Angels,</hi> practised by <hi>Cranmer, Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> (as <hi>Invocation</hi> of <hi>Saints</hi> was allowed by <hi>Bilney</hi> and <hi>Latimer,</hi> in their distinguishing between <hi>Mediators</hi> of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi> and <hi>Intercession,</hi> and granting that the <hi>later</hi> might be <hi>Prayed</hi> to, as such <hi>Mediators. Foxes Acts and Monuments,</hi> pag. <hi>462. 6 post Med.</hi> and p. <hi>1312. ab init.</hi> and p. <hi>1315. paulo ante med.</hi>) The Doctrine of the <hi>Mass</hi> being a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for the <hi>Living</hi> and <hi>Dead,</hi> the Practices of <hi>Wafer-Cakes,</hi> mingling <hi>Water</hi> with <hi>Wine,</hi> and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrating
<pb facs="tcp:56117:5"/> the <hi>Elements</hi> with <hi>Crossing,</hi> of <hi>Oyle</hi> in <hi>Baptism,</hi> of <hi>Chrysomes,</hi> of <hi>Exorcisms,</hi> of the <hi>Cross</hi> in <hi>Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and in <hi>Marriage,</hi> of <hi>Extreme Unction,</hi> and the Doctrine of the <hi>VII. Sacraments;</hi> as well as the Practices of <hi>Dirges, Masses</hi> of <hi>Requiem,</hi> and <hi>Prayers</hi> for the <hi>Dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since the <hi>First Reformers,</hi> and their <hi>Heirs</hi> have thus unfortunately divided in their Accounts of <hi>Popery,</hi> what shall we say has occasion'd the Difference? Is <hi>Popery</hi> changed, or the <hi>Reformation?</hi> Assuredly, there are no <hi>New Poperies,</hi> for if there were, that bold Demand so often made, to assign the <hi>Age</hi> in which any of their <hi>Errours</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, had long since received an Answer. It remains then, that there Are, and Have been <hi>New Reformations:</hi> I know it uses to be said for these <hi>New Reformations</hi> upon the <hi>Old,</hi> That the Case of the <hi>First Reformers</hi> resembl'd that of Men proceeding out of a dark <hi>Cave,</hi> and consequently the <hi>Light</hi> by which they acted,<note place="margin">(Holy Table Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and Thing. <hi>p. 93</hi>
               </note> such as the <hi>French-men</hi> calls, <hi>Entre Chien &amp; Loup,</hi> not sufficient to mark a <hi>Dog</hi> from a <hi>Woolf;</hi> which cannot but be very grateful News and an unspeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Comfort to all their <hi>Flock</hi> at once, Since it seems it is an even Wager, whether they are All <hi>Damned</hi> or <hi>Saved:</hi> As it passes a profound Complement upon the <hi>Reformation</hi> and <hi>Reformers,</hi> shall I say, or the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> by which they Acted; who it seems had Taught them that <hi>Prayer</hi> for the <hi>Dead, Chrysomes</hi> and <hi>Extreme Unction,</hi> were <hi>agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> to the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and to the <hi>Usages</hi> of the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church,</hi> and that the <hi>Mass</hi> was brought by them, <hi>even to the very Use as CHRIST left it, as the Apostles used it,</hi> and <hi>as the Holy Fathers delivered it;</hi> Ʋntil such time, as <hi>Calvin</hi> forsooth had better instructed the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> that I may not say the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> that the same were Reliques of the <hi>Popish Leaven,</hi> and as such to be left out of the <hi>New Liturgy,</hi> which came out <hi>three years</hi> after <hi>Anno 1552.</hi> As they were accordingly.</p>
            <p>So it was, that the <hi>First Reformers</hi> had the ill luck to venture on the work of <hi>Reformation,</hi> without consulting the
<pb facs="tcp:56117:5"/> Oracle of the <hi>Reformation:</hi> And <hi>Calvin</hi> taking pet that they advis'd with the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> rather than with <hi>Him;</hi> what could the Church of <hi>England</hi> do less, being thus unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily in the good Mans Displeasure, but to Court his Favour, fairly lay aside the <hi>Holy Ghost's Liturgy,</hi> to make way in good Manners for Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi>'s. Till in the end, after so many <hi>New Liturgies,</hi> they came to have <hi>None</hi> at all. For it is very observable, that the more the Church of <hi>Eng.</hi> land has enlarg'd her <hi>Phylacteries</hi> and made broad her <hi>Fringes,</hi> the more she has betrayed her <hi>Nakedness,</hi> her <hi>Dissenters</hi> having still increased upon her, in proportion to her multiplying her <hi>Liturgies:</hi> For as by changing her <hi>Old Liturgies</hi> for <hi>New,</hi> she lost the Company of the <hi>Old Papists</hi> to Court the <hi>Old Non-conformists,</hi> so by changing these again for <hi>Newer,</hi> at length she lost, even the Company of the <hi>New Non-conformists.</hi> Nor is the Success to be wondred at; for if men once came to be so bold as to find fault with the <hi>First</hi> which was the <hi>Work</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> much more would they venture to be bolder with the <hi>Later,</hi> which were own'd to be but the <hi>Works</hi> of <hi>Men.</hi> If the <hi>First Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers</hi> were in the <hi>Wrong,</hi> what Assurance have we, say the <hi>Dissenters,</hi> that the <hi>Later</hi> who boast not the same <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> are in the <hi>Right?</hi> Or if the <hi>First</hi> were so <hi>Blind,</hi> as to spy but <hi>some Errors</hi> of <hi>Popery;</hi> who knows whether their <hi>Heirs,</hi> who are but the <hi>Blind led by the Blind,</hi> have discover'd <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Errors</hi> of the <hi>Reformation?</hi> Since the same Fate attends all <hi>later Reformations</hi> upon the <hi>First,</hi> which uses to follow the Attempts of curing the <hi>Streams</hi> where the <hi>Spring</hi> is <hi>Impure,</hi> or of supporting a <hi>Building,</hi> whose <hi>Foundation</hi> is in the <hi>Sands.</hi> For the self same Reasons and Motives, which the <hi>First Reformers</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> make use of to colour <hi>Schism</hi> their from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> these <hi>Reformers</hi> of the <hi>Reformation</hi> serve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves of to colour their <hi>Schism</hi> from the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> concluding in such Cases, that if the <hi>Primitive Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> be not the <hi>Purest,</hi> that cannot fail to be so, which
<pb facs="tcp:56117:6"/> is the <hi>Latest.</hi> For if it appear'd an Error in the <hi>First Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> to use <hi>Prayers for the Dead,</hi> after disclaiming <hi>Purgatory</hi> which brought them in; what was it less in the <hi>Later</hi> to practise <hi>Bowing</hi> to the <hi>Altar,</hi> and enjoyn <hi>Kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> at the <hi>Communion,</hi> after renouncing <hi>Transubstantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which occasion'd <hi>Both.</hi> For which is the greater So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecism, to offer <hi>Prayers</hi> for those that <hi>need them not,</hi> or to give <hi>Divine Honour</hi> to what <hi>deserves it not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether the <hi>First Reformers</hi> would have taken the <hi>Test,</hi> is perhaps as great a Question, as whether those that have <hi>taken</hi> the <hi>Test,</hi> would have received their <hi>Liturgy:</hi> For upon a just Comparison of the <hi>Primitive Liturgy</hi> with the <hi>Present,</hi> the Case will be found much the same with that of <hi>Apelles</hi> his two <hi>Pieces.</hi> For that great <hi>Master</hi> having exposed an <hi>Original</hi> of his to the publick View of the gazing Crowd, they were not more concerned to hit all the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Blots</hi> which he made, than he was to <hi>Reform</hi> them all in another <hi>Piece</hi> that he prepared accordingly; which by being <hi>Reformed</hi> so often, proved so monstrous a <hi>Libel</hi> on his Art, as the <hi>Reformers</hi> laughing at their <hi>own Picture,</hi> no less than the <hi>Artist</hi> himself; he was obliged in his own Defence to produce the <hi>Original,</hi> and the <hi>Reformation</hi> together, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, <hi>Hanc ego feci, istam Populus, This</hi> is <hi>my Picture,</hi> and <hi>That</hi> is <hi>Yours.</hi> And were the <hi>First Reformers</hi> alive again that made the <hi>Old Liturgy,</hi> I perswade my self, they would make themselves as Merry with the <hi>New</hi> one, if they were not ready to dismiss them <hi>Both</hi> with the same pleasant Application.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56117:6"/>
            <head>AN EXTRACT OF THE First Liturgy OF King EDWARD VI. Set forth <hi>May</hi> 1549. in the Third year of K. <hi>Edward</hi>'s Reign; (whose Compilers were <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Ridley,</hi> &amp;c. Several of <hi>Foxes</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs) showing how far it was <hi>Popishly Affected.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Communion Office.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Supper of our Lord,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Communion,</hi> commonly called,<note place="margin">The Name of <hi>Mass.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>The Mass.</hi> (Fol. CX.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rubrick,</hi> Upon the Day, and at the Time appointed for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of the <hi>Holy Communion,</hi> the <hi>Priest</hi> that shall Execute the Holy Ministery, shall put upon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56117:7"/> him the <hi>Vesture</hi> appointed for that Ministration, that is to say,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Albe</hi> and <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles</hi> with a <hi>Cope.</hi>
                  </note> a <hi>White Albe plain,</hi> with a <hi>Vestment</hi> or <hi>Cope;</hi> and where there be many <hi>Priests</hi> or <hi>Deacons,</hi> then so many shall be ready to help the <hi>Priest</hi> in the Ministration, as shall be requisite. And shall have upon them likewise the <hi>Vestures</hi> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for their Ministry; that is to say, <hi>Albes</hi> with <hi>Tunacles. (Ibid.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rubrick,</hi> Then shall the <hi>Minister</hi> take so much <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> as shall Suffice the Persons appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Receive the <hi>Holy Communion,</hi> laying the <hi>Bread</hi> upon the <hi>Corporas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Paten <hi>and</hi> Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral.</note> or else upon the <hi>Paten;</hi> or in some other Comely thing prepar'd for that Purpose: And putting the <hi>Wine</hi> into the <hi>Chalice,</hi> or else into some fair or convenient <hi>Cup</hi> prepar'd for that Use, (if the <hi>Chalice</hi> will not serve;) putting thereto a little pure and clean <hi>Water.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Wine <hi>and</hi> Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> (<hi>Fol.</hi> CXIIII.)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Prayer.</head>
               <p>And here we do give unto thee, most high Praise and hearty Thanks, for the wonderful Grace and Vertue declar'd in all thy <hi>Saints</hi> from the Beginning of the World: And chiefly in the Glorious and most Blessed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</hi>
                  </note> Mother of thy Son <hi>Jesu Christ</hi> our Lord and God, and in the <hi>Holy Patriarchs, Prophets, Apostles,</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> whose Examples, (O Lord,) and Stedfastness in thy Faith and keeping thy Holy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, grant us to Follow: We Commend unto thy Mercy, O Lord, all other thy <hi>Servants</hi> which and <hi>Departed</hi> hence from us, with the <hi>Sign</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> and do now rest in the <hi>Sleep</hi> of <hi>Peace;</hi> Grant un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them we beseech thee,<note place="margin">Prayer for the <hi>Dead.</hi>
                  </note> thy <hi>Mercy</hi> and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting <hi>Peace;</hi> and that at the day of the <hi>General
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56117:7"/> Resurrection,</hi> We and All They which be of the <hi>Mystical Body</hi> of thy <hi>Son,</hi> may altogether be set on his <hi>Right-hand,</hi> and hear that his most joyful Voice, <hi>Come unto me, O ye that be Blessed of my Father, and possess the Kingdom which is prepared for you from the beginning of the World.</hi> (Fol. CXVI.)</p>
               <p>The <hi>Minister</hi> Consecrates the <hi>Elements,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Elements Consecrated with the <hi>Cross. Haec Dona, haec Muner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> with <hi>Crossing</hi> them at the Words, <hi>Bl</hi>✚<hi>ess and Sanc</hi>✚<hi>tify these thy Gifts and Creatures of</hi> Bread <hi>and</hi> Wine, <hi>that they may be unto us, the</hi> Body <hi>and</hi> Blood <hi>of thy dearly beloved Son Jesus Christ. (Ibid.)</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Prayer.</head>
               <p>And although we be Unworthy, through our manifold <hi>Sins,</hi> to offer unto thee any <hi>Sacrifice;</hi> yet we beseech thee to accept this our bound en Duty and Service; and command these our <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Supplications,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Invocation <hi>of</hi> Angels.</note> by the <hi>Ministry</hi> of thy Holy <hi>Angels</hi> to be brought up into thy <hi>Holy Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle,</hi> before the sight of thy <hi>Divine Majesty, (Fol. CXVIII.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rubrick,</hi> And when he delivers the Sacrament of the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> he shall say to every one these words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Body of our Lord Jesus Christ which was given for thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Corpus Domini nostri <hi>Jesu Christi</hi> custodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at Animam tuam in vitam Eternam.</note>
                  <hi>preserve thy Body and Soul unto Everlasting Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the <hi>Minister</hi> delivering the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Blood,</hi> and giving every one to <hi>Drink once,</hi> and no more. shall say,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Blood of our Lord Jesus Christ which was shed for thee, preserve thy Body and Soul unto everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Life. (Fol.</hi> CXVIII.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rubrick,</hi> For avoiding of all matters and occasion of Dissention, it is meet that the <hi>Bread</hi> prepar'd
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56117:8"/> for the <hi>Communion,</hi> be made through all this Realm,<note place="margin">Wafer-Cakes.</note> after <hi>one Sort</hi> and <hi>Fashion,</hi> that is to say, <hi>Ʋnleaven'd</hi> and <hi>Round</hi> as it was <hi>afore;</hi> but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all manner of <hi>Print,</hi> and something more <hi>larger,</hi> and <hi>thicker</hi> than it <hi>was;</hi> so that it may be aptly divided in divers <hi>Pieces,</hi> and every one shall be divided into <hi>two Pieces</hi> at the least or more, by the Discretion of the <hi>Minister,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Christus</hi> totus in tota &amp; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus in qualibet parte Hostiae</note> and so distributed. And men must not think <hi>less</hi> to be Received in <hi>Part,</hi> than in the <hi>Whole;</hi> but in each of them, the <hi>whole Body</hi> of our Saviour <hi>Jesus Christ.</hi> (Fol. CXXI.) <hi>Rubrick,</hi> And although it be Read in Antient Writers, <hi>That the People many years past, received at the</hi> Priests hands, <hi>the Sacraments of the</hi> Body <hi>of Christ in their</hi> own Hands, <hi>and</hi> no Commandment <hi>of Christ to the</hi> contrary: <hi>Yet for as much as they many times</hi> Convey'd <hi>the same secretly away,</hi> kept it <hi>with them, and diversly</hi> abus'd it <hi>to Superstition and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness; least any</hi> such thing <hi>hereafter should be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted; and that an</hi> Uniformity <hi>might be us'd throughout the whole Realm: It is thought conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient the People</hi> commonly <hi>receive the Sacrament of Christs Body in their</hi> Mouths,<note place="margin">The <hi>Host</hi> taken at the <hi>Priests Hand</hi> in their <hi>Mouths.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>at the</hi> Priests hands <hi>(Ibid.)</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Office of Publick <hi>Baptism.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rubrick,</hi> Here shall the <hi>Priest</hi> ask, <hi>What shall be the Name of the Child;</hi> and when the <hi>God-fathers</hi> and <hi>God-Mothers</hi> have told the <hi>Name,</hi> then he shall make a <hi>Cross</hi> upon the <hi>Childs Forehead</hi> and <hi>Breast,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Forehead</hi> and <hi>Breast</hi> signed in <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism.</hi>
                  </note> saying,</p>
               <p>N. <hi>Receive the Sign of the</hi> Holy Cross, <hi>both in thy</hi> Forehead <hi>and thy</hi> Breast; <hi>in token that thou shalt not be asham'd to confess thy Faith in Christ Crucified; and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56117:8"/> manfully to fight under his Banner against Sin, the World and the Devil: And to continue his Faithful Soldier and Servant unto thy Lifes end.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>And this he shall <hi>do</hi> and <hi>say,</hi> to as many <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> as be present to be <hi>Baptiz'd,</hi> one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Fol.</hi> CXXVI.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rubrick,</hi> Then the <hi>Priest</hi> shall take the <hi>Child</hi> in his Hands, and ask the <hi>Name.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Trina Immersio.</note> And naming the <hi>Child,</hi> shall <hi>dip</hi> it in the Water <hi>thrice; First,</hi> dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the <hi>Right-side; Second,</hi> the <hi>Left-side;</hi> the <hi>Third</hi> time dipping the <hi>Face,</hi> toward the Font, so it be discreetly and warily done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rubrick,</hi> And if the <hi>Child</hi> be <hi>weak,</hi> it shall suffice to <hi>pour Water</hi> upon it, saying the aforesaid words: <hi>N. I Baptize thee,</hi> &amp;c. Then the <hi>God-fathers</hi> and <hi>God-mothers</hi> shall take and lay their Hands upon the <hi>Child,</hi> and the <hi>Minister</hi> shall put upon him his <hi>Vesture,</hi> commonly call'd the <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some,</hi> and say,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take this</hi> White Vesture <hi>for a Token of the</hi> Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence,<note place="margin">Chrysomes.</note>
                  <hi>which by Gods Grace in this Holy Sacrament of</hi> Baptism <hi>is given unto thee: And for a Sign, whereby thou art Admonish'd so long as thou livest to give thy felf to</hi> Innocence <hi>of living: That after this transitory Life, thou mayest be partaker of the Life Everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>Then the <hi>Priest</hi> shall <hi>Anoint</hi> the Child upon the <hi>Head.</hi> saying,<note place="margin">Oyl in Baptism</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Almighty God, the Father of our Lord Christ, who has Regenerate thee by</hi> Water, <hi>and the</hi> Holy Ghost; <hi>and has given unto thee Remission of all thy Sins; He vouchsafe to Anoint with the</hi> Unction <hi>of his Holy Spirit, and bring thee to the Inheritance of Everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Life,</hi> Amen. (<hi>Fol.</hi> CXXVIII.)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:56117:9"/>
               <head>The Close of the Office of <hi>Private Baptism.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rubrick,</hi> The <hi>Water</hi> in the <hi>Font</hi> shall be chang'd, every Month <hi>once</hi> at least; and afore any <hi>Child</hi> be <hi>Baptiz'd</hi> in the <hi>Water</hi> so <hi>Chang'd,</hi> the <hi>Priest</hi> shall say at the <hi>Font</hi> these Prayers following.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O most Merciful God, our Saviour Jesu Christ, who hast Ordain'd the</hi> Element <hi>of</hi> Water <hi>for the</hi> Regeneration <hi>of thy Faithful People; upon whom being Baptiz'd in the River of</hi> Jordan,<note place="margin">Exorcisms.</note>
                  <hi>the</hi> Holy Ghost <hi>came down in the likeness of a</hi> Dove; <hi>Send down we beseech the same thy Holy Spirit to Assist us, and be Present at this our Invocation of thy Holy Name. Sanctify ✚ this</hi> Fountain <hi>of</hi> Baptism, <hi>Thou that art the Sanctifier of</hi> All Things, <hi>that by the Power of thy Word, all those that shall be</hi> Baptiz'd herein, <hi>may be</hi> Spiritually Regenerated, <hi>and made the</hi> Children <hi>of everlasting Adoption,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O merciful God, grant that the Old</hi> Adam <hi>in them that shall be</hi> Baptiz'd <hi>in this</hi> Fountain <hi>may so be</hi> Buried <hi>that the</hi> New Man <hi>may be</hi> Rais'd up <hi>again,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Grant that all</hi> Carnal Affections <hi>may</hi> die <hi>in them, and that all things belonging to the</hi> Spirit <hi>may</hi> live, <hi>and</hi> grow <hi>in them,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Grant unto all Them, which at this</hi> Fountain <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake the</hi> Devil <hi>and all his</hi> Works, <hi>that they may have Power and Strength to have Victory, and to Triumph against</hi> Him, <hi>the</hi> World <hi>and the</hi> Flesh, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whosoever shall</hi> Confess <hi>Thee, O Lord,</hi> Recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize <hi>him also in thy Kingdom,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Grant that all Sin and Vice here, may so be</hi> Extinct, <hi>that they never have Power to</hi> Raise <hi>in thy Servants,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:56117:9"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Grant, That whosoever here shall</hi> Begin <hi>to be of thy</hi> Flock, <hi>may evermore</hi> Continue <hi>in the same,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Grant that all They, which for thy sake in this Life do</hi> Deny <hi>and</hi> Forsake <hi>Themselves, may</hi> Winne <hi>and</hi> Purchase <hi>thee (O Lord,) which art</hi> Everlasting Treasure, Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Grant, That whosoever is here</hi> Dedicated <hi>to Thee by our Office and Ministry, may also be indued with Heavenly Vertues, and everlastingly Rewarded through thy Mercy; O Blessed Lord God, who dost live and Govern all things, world without End.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lord be with you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Answer,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And with thy Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Almighty ever living God, whose most dearly Beloved Son</hi> Jesus Christ <hi>for the forgiveness of our Sins, did shed out of his most</hi> precious Side, <hi>both</hi> Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>and</hi> Blood, <hi>and gave Commandment to his Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi> That they should Go teach all Nations, and Baptize them in the Name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghost. <hi>Regard we beseech the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of Thy Congregation; and grant that all thy</hi> Servants <hi>which shall be</hi> Baptiz'd <hi>in this</hi> Water, <hi>prepar'd for the Ministration of thy</hi> Holy Sacrament; <hi>may receive the Fullness of thy Grace, and ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the Number of thy Faithful and Elect Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: Through Jesus Christ our Lord.</hi> Amen. (<hi>Fol.</hi> CXXXII.)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Office of <hi>Confirmation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rubrick,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sureties in Confirmation.</note> Then shall they be brought to the <hi>Bishop,</hi> by one that shall be his <hi>God-father,</hi> or <hi>God-mother,</hi> that every <hi>Child</hi> may have a <hi>Witness</hi> of his <hi>Confirmation.</hi> (Fol. CXXXIV.)</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:56117:10"/>
               <p>Minister,</p>
               <p>Sign <hi>them, O Lord, and</hi> Mark <hi>them to be</hi> Thine <hi>for ever by the Vertue of thy</hi> Holy Cross <hi>and Passion,</hi> Confirm <hi>and</hi> Strengthen <hi>them with the</hi> Inward Unction <hi>of thy Holy Ghost, mercifully unto Everlasting Life.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>Then the <hi>Bishop</hi> shall <hi>Cross</hi> them in the <hi>Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,</hi> and lay his Hand upon their Head, saying.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cross <hi>in</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation.</note>
                  <hi>I Sign thee with the Sign of the</hi> Cross, <hi>and lay my Hand upon thee in the Name of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost.</hi> Amen. (<hi>Fol.</hi> CXXXV.)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Office of <hi>Matrimony.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rubrick,</hi> The <hi>Man</hi> shall give unto the <hi>Woman</hi> a <hi>Ring,</hi> and other Tokens of Spousage, as <hi>Gold,</hi> or <hi>Silver,</hi> laying the same upon the <hi>Book.</hi> And the <hi>Priest</hi> taking the <hi>Ring</hi> shall deliver it to the <hi>Man,</hi> to put it upon the <hi>fourth Finger</hi> of the <hi>Womans Left Hand;</hi> and the <hi>Man</hi> Taught by the <hi>Priest,</hi> shall say,</p>
               <p>With this Ring <hi>I thee Wed, this</hi> Gold <hi>and</hi> Silver <hi>I thee give, with my Body I thee Worship, and with all my Worldly Goods I thee Indow; In the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>Then the <hi>Man</hi> leaving the <hi>Ring</hi> upon the <hi>fourth Finger</hi> of the <hi>Womans Left Hand,</hi> the <hi>Minister</hi> shall say,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Let us Pray.</head>
               <p>O Eternal God, Creator and preserver of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; Giver of all Spiritual Grace, the Author of Everlasting Life, send thy Blessing upon these thy Servants, this <hi>Man</hi> and this <hi>Woman,</hi> whom we Bless in thy Name; that as <hi>Isaac</hi> and <hi>Rebecca,</hi> (after <hi>Bracelets</hi> and <hi>Jewels</hi> of <hi>Gold</hi>) given of one to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56117:10"/> other, for <hi>Tokens</hi> of their <hi>Matrimony,</hi> liv'd Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully together: So these <hi>Persons</hi> may surely perform and keep the <hi>Vow</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> betwixt them made, whereof this <hi>Ring</hi> given and receiv'd, is a <hi>Token</hi> and <hi>Pledge,</hi> and may ever Remain in perfect <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> together; and live according to thy Laws, Through Jesus Christ our Lord, <hi>Amen.</hi> (fol. <hi>cxxxvii.</hi>)</p>
               <p>Rubrick, <hi>Then shall the</hi> Priest <hi>joyn their</hi> Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hands <hi>together, and say,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Those whom <hi>God</hi> has joyn'd together, let no <hi>Man</hi> put asunder.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then shall the</hi> Minister <hi>speak unto the</hi> People. For as much as <hi>N.</hi> and <hi>N.</hi> have consented together in <hi>Holy Wedlock,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Marriage <hi>a</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</note> and have Witnessed the same here before <hi>God,</hi> and this <hi>Company:</hi> And thereto have given and pledg'd their <hi>Troth</hi> either to other; and have declar'd the same, by giving and receiving <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver,</hi> and by joyning of <hi>Hands:</hi> I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that they be <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Wife</hi> together: <hi>In the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the</hi> Minister <hi>shall add this</hi> Blessing.</p>
               <p>God the Father Bless ✚ you, God the Son keep you, God the Holy Ghost Lighten your Ʋnderstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. (Ibid.)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Let us Pray.</head>
               <p>O God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> God of <hi>Isaac,</hi> God of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> Bless these thy <hi>Servants,</hi> and sow the Seed of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56117:11"/> Eternal Life in their Minds; that whatsoever in thy <hi>Holy Word</hi> they shall Profitably Learn, they may in deed fullfil the same. Look, O Lord, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully upon them from Heaven, and Bless them: And as thou didst send thy Angel <hi>Raphael</hi> to <hi>Thobie</hi> and <hi>Sara,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(Tobit. 12)</note> the Daughter of <hi>Raguel,</hi> to their great Comfort; so vouchsafe to send thy Blessing upon these thy <hi>Servants,</hi> that they obeying thy Will, and always being in Safety, under thy Protection, may abide in thy Love, unto their Lives end; through Jesus Christ our Lord, <hi>Amen, (fol.</hi> cxxxviii.)</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cross <hi>in</hi> Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</note>And the <hi>Priest</hi> again Blesses the new Married <hi>Couple</hi> with the Sign of the <hi>Cross</hi> at the words, <hi>Bl✚ess, and Sanc✚tifie you. (fol.</hi> cxxxix.)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Office of <hi>Visitation</hi> of the <hi>Sick.</hi> Prayer.</head>
               <p>Hear us Almighty and most Merciful God and Saviour, extend thine accustom'd Goodness to this thy <hi>Servant</hi> which is griev'd with <hi>Sickness:</hi> Visit him, O Lord, as thou didst Visit <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Wives Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and the <hi>Captains Servant;</hi> and as thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servedst <hi>Thobie</hi> and <hi>Sara</hi> by thy <hi>Angel</hi> from Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,<note place="margin">(Tobit. 11.)</note> so Restore unto this <hi>Sick Person</hi> his former <hi>Health,</hi> if it be thy Will; or else, give him Grace so to take thy Correction, that after this <hi>Painful Life</hi> ended, he may dwell with thee, in <hi>Life Everlasting,</hi> Amen. (<hi>fol.</hi> cxli.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rubrick,</hi> If the <hi>Sick Person</hi> desire to be <hi>Anointed,</hi> then shall the <hi>Priest Anoint</hi> him upon the <hi>Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Extreme Uncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:56117:11"/> or <hi>Breast,</hi> only making the <hi>Sign</hi> of the <hi>Cross,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A Sacrament.</note> saying thus:<note place="margin">Outward Visible Sign, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Invisible Grace.</note>
                  <hi>As with this</hi> Visible Oyl <hi>thy</hi> Body Outwardly <hi>is</hi> Anointed, <hi>so our Heavenly Father Almighty God, grant of his Infinite Goodness, that thy</hi> Soul Inwardly <hi>may be</hi> Anointed <hi>with the</hi> Holy Ghost <hi>who is the</hi> Spirit <hi>of all</hi> Strength, Comfort, Relief <hi>and</hi> Gladness; <hi>And vouchsafe for his great Mercy, (if it be his Blessed Will) to restore unto thee thy Bodily</hi> Health <hi>and</hi> Strength <hi>to serve him: And send thee Release of all thy</hi> Pains, Troubles <hi>and</hi> Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases <hi>both in</hi> Body <hi>and</hi> Mind. (<hi>fol.</hi> cxliii, cxliv.)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Office of the <hi>Communion</hi> of the <hi>Sick.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If the same day there be a Celebration of the <hi>Holy Communion</hi> in the <hi>Church;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reservation of the <hi>Sacrament.</hi>
                  </note> then shall the <hi>Priest reserve</hi> (at the <hi>Open Communion</hi>) so much of the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of CHRIST's <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> as shall serve the <hi>Sick Person;</hi> and as <hi>Many</hi> as shall <hi>Communicate</hi> with him (if there be any) (<hi>fol.</hi> cxliv.)</p>
               <p>But if any man, either by reason of <hi>Extremity</hi> of <hi>Sickness,</hi> or for lack of <hi>Warning</hi> given in due time to the <hi>Curate,</hi> or by any other <hi>just Impediment</hi> do <hi>not Receive</hi> the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi>'s <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood:</hi> Then the <hi>Curate</hi> shall instruct him, that if he do truly <hi>Repent</hi> him of his Sins, and stedfastly <hi>Believe</hi> that Jesus Christ has suffer'd Death upon the <hi>Cross</hi> for him, and shed his <hi>Blood</hi> for his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; Earnestly <hi>Remembring</hi> the Benefits he has thereby, and giving him hearty Thanks there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore:<note place="margin">Spiritual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</note> He does Eat and Drink <hi>Spiritually</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of our Saviour Christ, profitably to his Souls health, although he does <hi>not Receive</hi> the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> with his <hi>Mouth. (fol.</hi> cxlv.)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:56117:12"/>
               <head>In the <hi>Office</hi> of <hi>Burial</hi> of the <hi>Dead.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rubrick,</hi> Then the <hi>Priest</hi> casting Earth upon the <hi>Corpes,</hi> shall say,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Soul</hi> of the <hi>Decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed</hi> to <hi>God.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>I commend thy</hi> Soul <hi>to God the Father Almighty, and thy</hi> Body <hi>to the Ground;</hi> Earth <hi>to</hi> Earth, Ashes <hi>to</hi> Ashes, Dust <hi>to</hi> Dust.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Let us Pray.</head>
               <p>We commend into thy Hands of <hi>Mercy,</hi> most Merciful Father, the <hi>Soul</hi> this our <hi>Brother De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted,</hi> N. &amp;c. (<hi>fol.</hi> cxlvii.)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Let us Pray.</head>
               <p>O Lord, with whom do <hi>Live</hi> the <hi>Spirits</hi> of them that be <hi>Dead;</hi> and in whom the <hi>Souls</hi> of them that be Elected, after they be <hi>Delivered</hi> from the <hi>Burden</hi> of this <hi>Flesh,</hi> be in <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city:</hi> Grant unto this thy <hi>Servant,</hi> that the <hi>Sins</hi> which be Committed in <hi>this World,</hi> be not Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him; but that he escaping the Gates of <hi>Hell,</hi> and pains of <hi>Eternal Darkness,</hi> may ever dwell in the <hi>Region</hi> of <hi>Light</hi> with <hi>Abraham, Isaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> in the place where there is <hi>No Weeping, Sorrow,</hi> nor <hi>Heaviness:</hi> And when that Dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful day of <hi>General Resurrection</hi> shall come, make him to <hi>Rise</hi> also with the <hi>Just</hi> and <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> and receive his <hi>Body</hi> again to <hi>Glory,</hi> then made <hi>Pure</hi> and <hi>Incorruptible:</hi> Set him on the <hi>Right-hand</hi> of thy Son <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> among thy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56117:12"/>
                  <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Elect:</hi> That then he may hear with them these most Sweet and Comfortable words; <hi>Come to me ye Blessed of my Father, possess the Kingdom which hath been prepar'd for you from the beginning of the World:</hi> Grant this, we beseech thee, O Merciful Father, through <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> our Mediator and Redeemer, <hi>Amen. (fol.</hi> cxlix.)</p>
               <p>There is a <hi>Set-Form</hi> of Celebration of the <hi>Holy Communion</hi> appointed upon occasion of the <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial</hi> of the <hi>Dead. (fol.</hi> cl.)<note place="margin">Masses for the Dead.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Close of the Office of <hi>Purification</hi> of <hi>Women.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rubrick,</hi> The <hi>Woman</hi> that is <hi>Purified,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chrysomes.</note> must offer her <hi>Chrysome</hi> and other accustom'd <hi>Offerings, (fol.</hi> clii.)</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Notes</hi> for the more plain <hi>Explication</hi> and Decent <hi>Ministration</hi> of Things contain'd in the <hi>Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whensoever the <hi>Bishop</hi> shall Celebrate the <hi>Holy Communion</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> or Execute any <hi>Other publick Ministration;</hi> He shall have upon him,<note place="margin">The <hi>Bishop</hi> with his <hi>Crosier</hi> in time of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciating.</note> besides his <hi>Rochet</hi> a <hi>Surpless,</hi> or <hi>Albe,</hi> and a <hi>Cope</hi> or <hi>Vestment,</hi> and also his <hi>Pastoral Staff</hi> in his <hi>Hand,</hi> or else <hi>Born,</hi> or holden by his <hi>Chaplain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As touching <hi>Kneeling, Crossing, Holding</hi> up of <hi>Hands, Knocking upon the Breast,</hi> and other <hi>Postures.</hi> They may be <hi>Ʋs'd,</hi> or <hi>Left,</hi> as every mans De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion serveth, without blame, (<hi>fol.</hi> clvii.)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:56117:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Testimonials</hi> of the <hi>Liturgy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Concerning this <hi>First Liturgy</hi> of King <hi>Edward,</hi> hear what that <hi>Statute,</hi> 2 <hi>Edw.</hi> VI. that inforc'd the said <hi>Book,</hi> says— <hi>To the intent a uniform, quiet and godly Order should be had concerning the Premisses [the King] hath appointed the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of</hi> Canterbury, (i. e. <hi>Cranmer) and certain of the most Learned and Discreet Bishops</hi> (i. e. <hi>Goodrick</hi> Bishop of <hi>Ely, Skip</hi> Bishop of <hi>Hereford, Thirlby</hi> Bishop of <hi>Westminster, Day</hi> Bishop of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester, Holbeck</hi> Bishop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> and <hi>Ridley</hi> Bishop of <hi>Rochester,) and other</hi> Learned Men <hi>of this Realm,</hi> (i. e. <hi>May</hi> Dean of St. <hi>Pauls, Taylor</hi> Dean of <hi>Lincoln, Haynes</hi> Dean of <hi>Exeter, Redman</hi> Dean of <hi>Westminster; Cox,</hi> King <hi>Edward</hi>'s Almo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and <hi>Robinson</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Leicester:) To consider and ponder the Premises; and thereupon having eye and respect to the most sincere and pure</hi> Christian Religion <hi>Taught by the</hi> Scripture, <hi>as to the Ʋsages in the</hi> Primitive Church; <hi>should draw and make one convenient and meet Order, Rite and Fashion of</hi> Common <hi>and</hi> Open Prayer, <hi>and</hi> Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration <hi>of the</hi> Sacraments; <hi>to be had and used in his Majesties Realm of</hi> England, <hi>and in</hi> Wales: The which at this Time, by the <hi>Aid</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghost (Note</hi> that) with one <hi>Ʋniform Agreement,</hi> is of them concluded, set forth and deliver'd to his Highness, to his great Comfort and Quietness of Mind, in a Book Intituled, <hi>The Book of Common Prayer and Administration of the Sacraments, and other Rites and Ceremonies of the Church, after the Ʋse of the Church of</hi> England: Thus speaks the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> that inforces it.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:56117:13"/>
               <p>And again <hi>Statute</hi> 5. <hi>Edw.</hi> VI. Speaking of the <hi>same Liturgy, — The said</hi> Book <hi>allowed to be</hi> Agreeable to <hi>the</hi> Word of God, <hi>and the</hi> Primitive Church: Thus even that <hi>Act</hi> that <hi>Repealed</hi> it.</p>
               <p>Hear the Testimony of Archbishop <hi>Bancroft;</hi> He speaking of this <hi>Liturgy,</hi> in a <hi>Sermon</hi> of his Preach'd at St. <hi>Paul's-Cross, Anno</hi> 1588. affirms of it, that it was Publish'd first <hi>with such Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as that it was accounted the Work of God:</hi> Thus that Archbishop, and more he could not have said, had he been the <hi>Inspired</hi> Archbishop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> or any of the other <hi>inspired Bishops,</hi> that in the Style of K. <hi>Edwards Parliament,</hi> drew it up by the <hi>Aid</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghost.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hear the Testimony of <hi>John Fox;</hi> he tells us, <q>That the <hi>Compilers</hi> of that <hi>Liturgy</hi> were command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the King to have as well an Eye and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect unto the most sincere and pure <hi>Christian Religion</hi> Taught by the <hi>Holy Scriptures;</hi> as also to the <hi>Ʋsages</hi> of the <hi>Primitive Church;</hi> and to draw up one convenient and meet <hi>Order,</hi> Rite and Fashion of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> to be had and used within the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and the Dominions of the <hi>same:</hi> And then adds, that <hi>Through the Aid of the Holy Ghost,</hi> and with one Uniform Agreement; they did conclude, set forth, and deliver to the King a Book in <hi>English,</hi> Entituled, <hi>A Book of Common-Prayer,</hi> &amp;c.</q> Thus <hi>Foxe Acts</hi> and <hi>Monuments, Part</hi> 2. p. 660. And who fitter than <hi>John Foxe</hi> to give Testimony of his own
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56117:14"/>
                  <hi>Martyrs,</hi> the Compilers of this <hi>Liturgy,</hi> which <hi>Bancroft</hi> tells us, was receiv'd at its coming forth as the <hi>Work of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lastly,</hi> Hear the Word of a <hi>King;</hi> Even of King <hi>Edward</hi> himself, of his <hi>Own Liturgy;</hi> In his <hi>Answer</hi> to the <hi>Devonshire Rebels:</hi> 'For the <hi>Mass</hi> (for so is that <hi>Liturgy</hi> call'd in the <hi>Book</hi> itself, (p. 110.) as also in the <hi>Statute</hi> that inforc'd it, 2 <hi>Edward</hi> VI. and in King <hi>Edwards Injunctions, Injunct.</hi> 21.) <q>I assure you▪ (says he) no small Study nor Travel has been spent by all the Learned <hi>Clergy</hi> therein; and to avoid all Contention, <hi>It is brought even to the very Ʋse as</hi> Christ <hi>left it, as the</hi> Apostles <hi>used it, as the</hi> Holy Fathers <hi>Deliver'd it:</hi>
                  </q> Thus King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> of that Book, which as his <hi>Parliament</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presses it, was set forth to his <hi>great Comfort</hi> and <hi>Quietness of Mind. Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon. Part.</hi> 2 p. 667.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:56117:14"/>
            <head>WISHES OF SEVERAL Churches &amp; Churchmen, FOR THE Restoring several PARTS OF THE First Liturgy OF K. EDWARD VI. <hi>For the Name of</hi> Mass.</head>
            <p>POpe <hi>Hyginus,</hi> the Eighth after S. <hi>Peter,</hi> insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, <hi>Ne Basilica sine</hi> Missâ <hi>Consecretur. That no Church be Consecrated without a</hi> Mass — And when the Bishop <hi>Panigarola</hi> says in his <hi>Sermon</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Whitsunday, That the</hi> Holy Ghost <hi>found the</hi> Blessed Virgin <hi>and the</hi> Apostles <hi>at</hi> Mass: I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume he means no more, then that they were met at such <hi>publick Prayer,</hi> as at those Times they might make. Sure Pope <hi>Clemens</hi> and Pope <hi>Hyginus</hi> mean the same thing, when one says, <hi>Missa Consecretur,</hi> and the other, <hi>Divinis Precibus:</hi> One says, <hi>Let the Consecration be with a</hi> Mass, the other, <hi>With
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56117:15"/> Divine Service,</hi> the <hi>Liturgy;</hi> The <hi>Divine Service</hi> was then the <hi>Mass.</hi> As Dr. <hi>Donne (Serm.</hi> in S. <hi>John</hi> 10.22.) more warily expresses it, instead of the <hi>Mass</hi> was then the <hi>Divine Service.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> in his Discourse of <hi>Churches since the Apostles times,</hi> among his <hi>Proofs for Churches in the second Century,</hi> produces a Testimony from the 1 <hi>Epistle</hi> of <hi>Pius</hi> the I. Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Justus Viennensis,</hi> about the <hi>Middle</hi> of that <hi>Century,</hi> and extant <hi>in Bibliotheca Patrum Tom.</hi> 1. which speaks as follows, <hi>Antequam</hi> Româ <hi>exiises,</hi> (says he) <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror nostra</hi> Euprepia <hi>(sicut bene recordaris) Titulum domus suae Pauperibus assignavit: Ʋbi nunc cum Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peribus nostris Commorantes</hi> Missas <hi>agimus. E're you left</hi> Rome, <hi>our Sister</hi> Euprepia <hi>(as you remember well) consigned the Title of her House to the</hi> Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: <hi>Where we being on the Place with the</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, <hi>say</hi> Mass: And then for fear of proving <hi>Masses since the Apostles Times</hi> as well as <hi>Churches,</hi> after his endeavours to clear his Testimony from suspicion, by affirming that it is such a one, as <hi>no man hath yet, that he knows of, proved to be suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitious,</hi> he adds his palliating Gloss in the Margent. <hi>The word</hi> Missa, <hi>seems to have been long used in</hi> Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>before it was elsewhere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vocabulum [Missa] certe</hi> Latinum <hi>est, &amp; inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum circa</hi> finem <hi>ut videtur,</hi> Tertii Seculi, <hi>vel Paulo</hi> ante: <hi>Nam si vera est</hi> Epistola Cornelii <hi>Papae ad</hi> Lupicinum Viennensem, <hi>circa</hi> Annum Domini 250. <hi>Notum jam erat istud</hi> Vocabulum <hi>ut recte ait</hi> Casaubonus, <hi>ubi supra. Neque à</hi> Missae <hi>nomine abhorrent Protestantes aequiores ut ex</hi> Confessione Augustanâ, &amp; Rituali Anglicanae Ecclesiae, <hi>in quo legere est Nomina illa</hi> (Christmass &amp; Michaëlmas)
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56117:15"/>
               <hi>Missa</hi> CHRISTI, <hi>&amp; Missa</hi> Michaëlis, <hi>evidenter patet. Forbesii Cosiderationes Pacificae &amp; Modestae</hi> l. 3. <hi>de Sacrificio</hi> Missae <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>The Term</hi> [Mass] <hi>is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly</hi> Latine, <hi>and came in, as it should seem; about the</hi> End <hi>of the</hi> Third Century, <hi>or a little</hi> earlier. <hi>For if that</hi> Epistle <hi>be Genuine of Pope</hi> Cornelius <hi>to</hi> Lupicinus Viennensis, <hi>that Term had got Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance about the year</hi> 250. <hi>As</hi> Casaubon <hi>right ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves, above. Nor do the more moderate Protestants</hi> (says Bishop <hi>Forbes) startle at the Name of</hi> Mass. <hi>As appears plain from the</hi> Auspurg Confession <hi>and the</hi> English <hi>Liturgy, where you meet with thee Names</hi> Christmass <hi>and</hi> Michaelmass, <hi>for the</hi> Mass of CHRIST, <hi>and the</hi> Mass of S. Michael.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For <hi>Copes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Copes</hi> are yet in Use in the Service of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral Church of <hi>Durham,</hi> if not in that of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Paten <hi>and</hi> Corporal, <hi>Name and Thing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Have you a <hi>Dish</hi> or <hi>Paten</hi> for the <hi>Bread:</hi> As also a <hi>Corporas</hi> Cloth, or Napkin of fine Linnen, to cover the <hi>Bread Consecrated,</hi> which cannot <hi>all at once</hi> be contain'd in the <hi>Paten,</hi> and to fold up all what is not used at <hi>Communion?</hi> Is an <hi>Article</hi> of Bishop <hi>Montague</hi> in his <hi>Articles of Visitation</hi> for the Diocess of <hi>Norwich</hi> in the year 1638. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. of <hi>Church Ʋtensils, Art.</hi> 20.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For <hi>Wafer-Cakes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wafer-Cakes</hi> were re-establish'd by the <hi>Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and continued in Use some time after. Nor is it likely that they were ever
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56117:16"/> displaced at first by Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> since they are in Use even at this present in his own pure Church of <hi>Geneva.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For <hi>Wine and Water,</hi> or a <hi>Mingled Chalice.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The practice of <hi>Mingling Wine and Water</hi> in the <hi>Chalice,</hi> had place in His <hi>Majesties Chappel Royal,</hi> all the time that Bishop <hi>Andrews</hi> was Dean of the said <hi>Chappel.</hi> Nay, in that Testimony which they have so often triumphed in, and which was therefore publish'd first and attested with so much Solemnity, by the Names and Subscriptions upon Record, of the Archbishops of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> the Bishops of <hi>London, Durham, Winchester,</hi> &amp;c. in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Days, I mean Abbot <hi>Aelfrikes Saxon Homily</hi> upon <hi>Easter,</hi> we are told that— <hi>Holy Books command that</hi> Water <hi>be mingled to the</hi> Wine <hi>which shall be for</hi> Housel (<hi>i. e. the</hi> Host) <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the</hi> Water <hi>signifies the</hi> People, <hi>and the</hi> Wine CHRIST<hi>'s</hi> Blood. And therefore shall neither the <hi>One</hi> without the <hi>Other</hi> be offer'd at the <hi>Holy Mass</hi> (so as S. <hi>Cyprian Epist. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Epist.</hi> 3. <hi>ad Caeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium</hi> requires) that CHRIST may be with Us, and We with CHRIST, the Head with the Limbs; and the Limbs with the Head. — Thus Abbot <hi>Aelfrike</hi> for his Time, which was about 700 years since. Nay some of the <hi>Reformed Writers</hi> themselves, doubt not to apply that of <hi>Proverbs</hi> 9.2. <hi>Wisdom has mingled her Wine, she has also furnish'd her Table;</hi> to this purpose, esteeming it no other then a Prediction of our Blessed Lords Institution of the <hi>Blessed Sacrament:</hi> So in particular, <hi>Ashwel</hi> on the <hi>Communion,</hi> as many of the <hi>Antient Fathers</hi> had apply'd it before, So <hi>Rabbi Samuel Marochianus,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:56117:16"/> who liv'd in the year 1070. and was a <hi>Converted Jew,</hi> and is extant in the <hi>Bibliotheca Patrum, Tom.</hi> 9. p. 421. <hi>What is this</hi> Table (says he, <hi>de Adventu Messiae</hi> c. 20.) <hi>the</hi> Wisdom <hi>of the most High has furnish'd, but the</hi> Altar? <hi>What is this</hi> Bread <hi>and</hi> mingled Wine, <hi>but the</hi> Sacrifice <hi>of</hi> Bread, Wine <hi>and</hi> Water, <hi>which is offered on the</hi> Altar? Thus he and so long before him S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited Epistle to <hi>Caecilius;</hi> who calls it our <hi>Lords Tradition,</hi> and as such, requires it to be observed. <hi>Dominica Traditio servetur.</hi> Upon which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion the late Bishop of <hi>Chester,</hi> in his Edition of that <hi>Father,</hi> being otherwise at a loss to Defend their <hi>Half-Cup,</hi> of <hi>Wine without Water,</hi> is driven in his <hi>Notes</hi> on that <hi>Epistle,</hi> to serve himself of one or two wretched Palliations; as first, he Notes the different practice of the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Latines</hi> in the <hi>mingled Chalice,</hi> observing from <hi>Balsamon</hi> that the <hi>Greeks</hi> mingle <hi>Warm Water,</hi> as the <hi>Latines, Cold:</hi> But will any gather a concluding Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence from hence, for <hi>Neither?</hi> In some late <hi>Councils</hi> it is left indifferent, to Administer <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism</hi> in <hi>Warm Water,</hi> or <hi>Cold;</hi> now will any take occasion from hence to Administer it in <hi>No Water.</hi> This Refuge failing him, his next Evasion is yet more frigid. He says, <hi>The</hi> Canon <hi>only requires</hi> Modicum Aquae; as if in his Logick, <hi>None at all,</hi> and so <hi>Little,</hi> as <hi>next to None,</hi> were all one. Let us try the force of his Argument in another In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, That is, in his own Church-Custom of <hi>Baptizing</hi> by a slender <hi>Sprinkling,</hi> since the <hi>Non-user</hi> of <hi>Immersion.</hi> It may be said alike, that there is but <hi>Modicum Aquae.</hi> And then making the same Inference, that <hi>None,</hi> and what is so <hi>Little,</hi> as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56117:17"/>
                  <hi>next to None,</hi> comes all to one. And so by one and the same Argument, our Blessed Lords <hi>Institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> may be evacuated both in the <hi>One,</hi> and in the <hi>Other Sacrament</hi> at once.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the <hi>Mass</hi>'s being a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for the <hi>Living</hi> and the <hi>Dead.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Once</hi> Suffer'd CHRIST by Himself, but yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the less his <hi>Suffering</hi> is <hi>Daily Renewed</hi> at the <hi>Mass,</hi> through the Mystery of the Holy <hi>Housel</hi> (or <hi>Host.</hi>) Therefore that Holy <hi>Mass</hi> is profitable both to the <hi>Living</hi> and the <hi>Dead:</hi> As it has been often declar'd. So <hi>Abbot Aelfrike,</hi> who lived in the year 990. in his fore-cited <hi>Saxon Homily</hi> on <hi>Easter:</hi> An Author, the rather to be esteem'd, as having had no less than the <hi>two Archbishops</hi> and 13. of Q. <hi>Elizabeths Bishops</hi> at once for his Vouchers upon his first Publication, been Printed more than once: And as being of that Reputation and Authority with Bishop <hi>Forbes,</hi> Bishop <hi>Bramhal,</hi> and the more Celebrated Writers of the <hi>English Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants;</hi> as that they doubt not to challenge him for their <hi>Own.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>More plainly yet, that the <hi>Mass</hi> is a Sacrifice for the <hi>Dead;</hi> meaning by the <hi>Dead,</hi> even the <hi>Souls</hi> in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> is no less evident than that it is a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for the <hi>whole Church;</hi> if we receive <hi>John Wickliffs</hi> Definition of the <hi>whole Church,</hi> who tells us, that <hi>General Holy Church is the Congregation of</hi> CHRIST, <hi>that is Head, and all good Angels in Heaven, and all Men and Women in</hi> Earth, <hi>or in</hi> Purgatory, <hi>that shall be saved and no more.</hi> Thus <hi>Wickliff,</hi> who liv'd in the year, 1371. in his Treatises against the Orders of <hi>Begging Fryars,</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:56117:17"/> Printed at <hi>Oxford</hi> in the year 1608. <hi>cap.</hi> 39. on occasion of the <hi>Article</hi> of CHRIST's Holy <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For <hi>Invocation</hi> of <hi>Angels.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O ye <hi>Blessed Spirits,</hi> ye are ever <hi>by</hi> me, ever <hi>with</hi> me, ever <hi>about</hi> me: I do as good as see you, for I know you to be here; I reverence your <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Persons,</hi> I Bless God for you; I walk <hi>Aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,</hi> because I am ever in your <hi>Eyes:</hi> I walk <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently,</hi> because I am ever in your <hi>Hands.</hi> How should I be asham'd, that in this piece of <hi>Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> I should be out-bid by very <hi>Turks,</hi> (citing <hi>Blunt</hi>'s Voyage to the <hi>Levant</hi> in the Margent,) whose <hi>Priests</hi> shut up their <hi>Devotions</hi> with an <hi>Appreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory,</hi> mention of your <hi>Presence;</hi> as if this were the up-shot of all Blessings; I am sure it is that, wherein <hi>next</hi> to my <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Saviour,</hi> I shall ever place my greatest <hi>Comfort</hi> and <hi>Confidence;</hi> neither has Earth or Heaven any other besides, that looks <hi>like it.</hi> So Bishop <hi>Hall</hi> in his Treatise of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visible World.</hi> l. 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Again, This <hi>Devotion</hi> we do gladly profess to owe to <hi>good Angels</hi> (he speaks here in the Name of his <hi>Church</hi>) that though we do not Pray unto them, yet we do Pray to God for the Favour of their <hi>Assistance</hi> and <hi>Protection;</hi> and Praise God for the <hi>Protection</hi> that we have from them. That Faithful <hi>Patriarch,</hi> of whom the whole Church of God receives Denomination, knew what he said, when he gave this <hi>Blessing</hi> to his <hi>Grand-Children: The Angel that Redemed me from all Evil, Bless the Children.</hi> Whether this were an interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive kind of Imploration, as <hi>Becanus</hi> and <hi>Lorichius</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:56117:18"/> contend; or whether (as it is no less Probable) this <hi>Angel</hi> were not any Created Power, but the great <hi>Angel</hi> of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> the same which <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> wrestled with before, for a <hi>Blessing</hi> upon <hi>Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self;</hi> as S. <hi>Athanasius</hi> and <hi>Cyril</hi> well conceive it, I will not here dispute. Sure I am, if it were an implicite Prayer, and the <hi>Angel</hi> mention'd a <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> (it seems he is not sure of the Contrary) yet the Intention was no other then to Terminate that <hi>Prayer</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> who Blesses us by his <hi>Angel</hi> (which is a kind of <hi>Popish Logick,</hi> in behalf of a <hi>Popish Practice.</hi>) He proceeds, — yet further, we come short of our <hi>Duty</hi> to these <hi>Blessed Spirits</hi> (says he) if we entertain not in our hearts an high and vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Conceit of their wonderful <hi>Majesty, Glory</hi> and <hi>Greatness,</hi> and an awful acknowledgement and reverential Awe of their <hi>Presence;</hi> an Holy Joy to do ought that might Cause them, to turn away their <hi>Faces</hi> in <hi>Dislike</hi> from us. Thus the <hi>same Bishop, Sect.</hi> 9. of the <hi>same Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But because the <hi>Devotion</hi> to <hi>Angels</hi> is an imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Consequence of the Doctrine of <hi>Guardian Angels,</hi> as being but a grateful Acknowledgement of the same. Instead of the Sense of a <hi>single Bishop,</hi> take that of the <hi>whole Church</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> so far as it appears from her <hi>present Liturgy;</hi> where all the <hi>Alterations</hi> and <hi>Reviews</hi> notwithstanding, the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect</hi> for <hi>Michaelmass-day,</hi> is with no greater Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, or Variation from that in the <hi>Missal,</hi> than follows.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Collect, for the Feast of <hi>S. Michael</hi> and all Angels.</head>
               <p>O Everlasting God, who hast Ordain'd and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted the Services of <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Men</hi> in won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56117:18"/>
                  <hi>Order:</hi> Mercifully grant, that as thy <hi>Holy Angels</hi> always do <hi>Thee Service</hi> in <hi>Heaven,</hi> so by thy Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they may <hi>Succour</hi> and <hi>Defend Ʋs</hi> on <hi>Earth,</hi> through JESUS CHRIST <hi>our Lord,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>To which we shall only add, what <hi>Sparrow</hi> in his <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionale</hi> hath upon the <hi>same Feast:</hi>
                  <q>Holy Church <hi>(says he)</hi> holds a <hi>Feast</hi> in memory of the <hi>Holy Angels.</hi> First, Because they Minister to us on Earth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Being sent forth to Minister to them that shall be Heirs of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> Secondly, Because they fight against the <hi>Devil</hi> for us, by their <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Recommendation</hi> of us and our Condition at the <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> as appears by the <hi>Epistle</hi> and the <hi>Gospel</hi> in the end of it. The Church in <hi>this Feast,</hi> particularly Commemorates S. <hi>Michael,</hi> because he was <hi>Prince,</hi> or <hi>Tutelar Angel</hi> of the Church of the <hi>Jews, Dan.</hi> 10.13.12.1. and so of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Church:</hi> For the Church which was once in the <hi>Jews,</hi> is now in the <hi>Christians.</hi>
                  </q> So <hi>Sparrow</hi>'s <hi>Rationale</hi> on the <hi>Feast</hi> of S. <hi>Michael.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the <hi>Invocation</hi> of our B. <hi>Lady.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>It seems to me impossible, that we should be Rewarded with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Intercession of the Virgin</hi> Mary. So far goes <hi>John Wickliff. In Serm. de Assump. Mariae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For Administring the <hi>Sacrament</hi> with this Form of Words. <hi>The Body of our Lord</hi> JESUS CHRIST,— <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve thy Body and Soul to everlasting Life;</hi> rather than with the Addition of <hi>Take, eat this in Remembrance,</hi> &amp;c. To give it the contrary Form of a bare <hi>Commemoration:</hi> And how the <hi>Additional Form</hi> came in.</p>
               <p>Whether the <hi>Sacrament</hi> with them has varied oftner its <hi>Seat,</hi> or its <hi>Notion,</hi> may be a Question. For the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of its <hi>Seat,</hi> hear <hi>Miles Huggard.</hi>
                  <q>How long were they learning to set their <hi>Table,</hi> to Minister the said <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:56117:19"/> upon? <hi>First,</hi> They placed it <hi>aloft,</hi> where the <hi>High-Altar</hi> stood? <hi>Then</hi> must it be set <hi>from</hi> the <hi>Wall,</hi> that one might go between: The <hi>Ministers</hi> being in Contention, on whether <hi>Part</hi> to turn their <hi>Faces,</hi> either towards the <hi>West,</hi> the <hi>North,</hi> the <hi>South;</hi> some would stand <hi>Westward,</hi> some <hi>Nothward,</hi> some <hi>Southward:</hi>
                  </q> Thus <hi>Miles Huggard,</hi> Displaying of <hi>Protestants, Anno</hi> 1556. p. 81. And for the variety of its <hi>Notion,</hi> hear <hi>Peter Heylin:</hi>
                  <q>The words of <hi>Distribution,</hi> retain'd in the first <hi>Liturgy</hi> of King <hi>Edward</hi> the VI and formerly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scrib'd to be used in the Antient <hi>Missals;</hi> that is to say, <hi>The Body of our Lord</hi> JESUS CHRIST, <hi>which was given for thee, preserve thy Body and Soul unto Life Everlasting The Blood of our Lord</hi> JESUS CHRIST, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which words being thought by some precise and scrupulous Persons to incline too much towards. <hi>Transubstantiation,</hi> were quite omitted in the <hi>second Liturgy</hi> of that King, <hi>Anno</hi> 1552. when <hi>Dudly</hi> of <hi>Northumberland</hi> who fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured the <hi>Calvinian</hi> Party carried all before him; the void place being fill'd up with the words of <hi>Participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> viz. <hi>Take, and eat this in Remembrance that</hi> CHRIST <hi>died for thee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Take, and drink this in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance,</hi> &amp;c. An <hi>Alteration</hi> (says he) not well grounded, and of short Continuance: For when that <hi>Book</hi> was brought under a <hi>Review,</hi> in the first year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> those words of the <hi>Distribution</hi> were restor'd to their former Place, and followed by those of the <hi>Participation,</hi> as it still continues. So <hi>Respondet Petrus,</hi> p. 104, 105.</q> By which Account it appears, that K. <hi>Edward</hi>'s <hi>first Liturgy</hi> was fram'd to Court the <hi>Catholicks</hi> with Words that carried a Sound of <hi>Transub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiation:</hi> His <hi>Second</hi> to Court the <hi>Calvinists,</hi> shall I say, or rather <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> and the <hi>Zwinglian</hi> Party with words that carried a sound of the <hi>Sacramentarian</hi> Doctrine of <hi>Commemoration:</hi> And then came Q. <hi>Elizabeths Liturgy</hi> which play'd the <hi>Trimmer</hi> to please both <hi>Parties,</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:56117:19"/> and tacked both the <hi>Formes</hi> together, of two contrary Sounds, of <hi>Transubstantiation</hi> and <hi>Commemoration.</hi> I call these Formes, <hi>The Body of our Lord</hi> JESUS CHRIST <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve thy Body and Soul to everlasting Life:</hi> And, <hi>Take, Eat this in Remembrance,</hi> &amp;c. two contrary Sounds: Because, as they justled out one another in K. <hi>Edward</hi>'s two <hi>Liturgies:</hi> So have they carried on a War ever since, between two <hi>Texts</hi> of a seeming Contrariety, <hi>viz. This is my Body;</hi> and, <hi>Do this in Remembrance of me:</hi> All the Arguments rais'd in favour of <hi>Transubstantiation</hi> from <hi>one Text,</hi> being duly answered with<note n="*" place="margin">We must take head least of the <hi>Memory,</hi> it be made a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,</hi> Homil. <hi>1. of the</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</note>
                  <hi>Commemoration</hi> in the <hi>other.</hi> And that which speaks the Language of three <hi>Gospels,</hi> and of S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Epistles</hi> being justled out by that which was deliver'd but in <hi>one Gospel,</hi> and there but after <hi>One Element,</hi> with as good reason, as, <hi>The Body of our Lord</hi> JESUS CHRIST, &amp;c. <hi>preserve thy Body and Soul unto Everlasting Life;</hi> in K. <hi>Edward</hi>'s <hi>First Liturgy</hi> was made to give way to, <hi>Take, Eat this in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance,</hi> &amp;c. in his <hi>Second.</hi> And with what Justice that Change was made, may be consider'd from <hi>John Wickliff.</hi>
                  <q>A man may have the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Auter,</hi> and that is <hi>very Gods Body</hi> in his Mouth, and straight flee to <hi>Hell</hi> withouten end; and the more be <hi>Damned</hi> for the <hi>Evil Taking</hi> of this <hi>Sacrament.</hi>
                  </q> Thus <hi>Wickliff</hi> in his fore-cited Treatise against the <hi>Orders</hi> of <hi>Begging-Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, cap.</hi> 20. And <hi>Wickliff</hi> all know, was no less one of <hi>Foxes Martys,</hi> than some of the Reverend Compilers of K. <hi>Edward</hi> the VI's <hi>Liturgy.</hi> Nay, as much one of the <hi>First Reformers,</hi> as even they <hi>Themselves,</hi> if we may believe some <hi>Protestant Writers:</hi> Though, if <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant</hi> he were; yet as far as we can learn from <hi>this,</hi> and the <hi>fore-going Passage,</hi> not a <hi>Protestant</hi> at least, according to the Form of the late <hi>Test.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Greek</hi> Church concurrs with <hi>Rome</hi> in the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Transubstantiation,</hi> in <hi>Praying to Saints,</hi> in Offering <hi>Sacrifices</hi> and <hi>Prayer</hi> for the <hi>Dead;</hi> as is affirm'd by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56117:20"/> Sir <hi>Edwin Sands,</hi> in his <hi>Europae Speculum,</hi> pag. 233. To whom we may add the Testimony of Bishop <hi>Forbes,</hi> who having spoken of the Evidence of the Patriarch <hi>Cyril,</hi> subjoyns these words, <hi>Sed quicquid hac de re senserit</hi> Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillus, <hi>certum est recentiores</hi> Graecos Transubstantiationis <hi>Opinione non fuisse, ne{que} etiamnum esse omnino Alienos. Hosce autem Omnes Christianae Pietatis Cultores,</hi> Haereseos aut Erroris Exitialis <hi>damnare, magnae profecto est Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daciae &amp; Temeritatis. Forbesii Considerationes Pacificae &amp; Modestae. De Eucharistia,</hi> l. 1. c. 4. <q>But whatever <hi>Cyril</hi> thought of the Matter, (says he) it is certain that the <hi>Modern Greeks</hi> neither were, nor are as yet Averse to the Opinion of <hi>Transubstantiation.</hi> But to Arraign all thse Christians at once, as guilty of <hi>Heresie</hi> or <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Error,</hi> is, without doubt, too Bold and Rash an Undertaking: Thus He.</q> And so we shall leave the <hi>Test,</hi> and those that have <hi>taken</hi> it, to Answer for themselves, as well as they can.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the <hi>Chrysomes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Light</hi> was imitated by the <hi>White Garment</hi> received in <hi>Baptism,</hi> as the Emperours expound it in <hi>Theodosians</hi> Code; <hi>Coelestis Lamen Lavacri imitantis novam Sanctae</hi> Baptismatis <hi>Lucem Vestimenta testantur. Cod. Theod. de Spectac.</hi> So the <hi>Priest</hi> in the Order of <hi>Severus, Change</hi> (says he, bespeaking the <hi>New Converts) your Garments, and be White as Snow, and let the Light shine as the Angels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Remaining yet unto us of this, is that which we more commonly call <hi>Chrysome (ab Ʋnctione,</hi> as the <hi>Manual,</hi> &amp;c.) wherewith the <hi>Women</hi> use to shrowd the <hi>Child,</hi> if dying within the <hi>Month.</hi> Otherwise it is to be brought to the Church, at the day of <hi>Purification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But by an <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Baptism</hi> in <hi>Edward</hi> the VI's <hi>Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> of the year 1549. it was to be put upon the <hi>Child</hi> at the <hi>Font,</hi> for the <hi>Rubrick</hi> is, <hi>Then the Godfathers and Godmothers shall take and lay their Hands upon the Child,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56117:20"/> and the Minister shall put upon him</hi> his White Vesture <hi>commonly called the</hi> Chrysome, <hi>and say,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take this White Vesture for a token,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And good Reason, for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>White</hi> does best become the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Light, Clemens Alexandrinus.</hi> Thus far Mr. <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Christ-Church Oxon</hi> in his Notes and Observations on Passages of <hi>Scripture, cap.</hi> 22. <hi>On the Meaning and Considerations of Light in Scripture;</hi> who is thought fit to deserve a place among the <hi>Volumes</hi> of the <hi>Criticks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Low-Sunday,</hi> in <hi>Latine, Dominica in Albis,</hi> or rather, <hi>Post Albas (sc. depositas)</hi> as some <hi>Old Rituals</hi> call it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause those that were <hi>Baptiz'd</hi> on <hi>Easter-Eve,</hi> wore seven days after, white Garments, called <hi>Chrysomes,</hi> Signs of the Purity which they receiv'd in <hi>Baptism:</hi> Which <hi>White Cloathes</hi> they this day put off; so <hi>Sparrow</hi>'s <hi>Rationale</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Low-Sunday.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the <hi>Exorcismes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>After the <hi>Abrenunciations</hi> (in the present <hi>Liturgy</hi>) fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low certain short Prayers, <hi>O merciful God,</hi> &amp;c. which I conceive to be the same in Substance, with the <hi>Antient Exorcisms,</hi> which were certain <hi>Prayers</hi> taken out of <hi>Holy Scripture, Cyril cap.</hi> 2. and composed by the Church. CONC. CARTH. 4. c. 1. for the <hi>Dispossessing</hi> of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to be <hi>Baptiz'd,</hi> who being <hi>Born</hi> in <hi>Sin,</hi> is under the <hi>Devils Tyranny,</hi> from which the <hi>Church</hi> by her <hi>Prayers</hi> endeavours to <hi>free</hi> him: And so available they were, that oftentimes those that were <hi>Corporally possessed;</hi> were <hi>freed</hi> by them, <hi>Cyprian Epist.</hi> 77. And thereupon <hi>Cyril, Nazianzen, Gennadius</hi> and others, earnestly persuade not to despise the <hi>Churches Exorcismes.</hi> That it was <hi>Antient</hi> to use these <hi>Exorcismes</hi> before <hi>Baptism, Nazianzen, in Lavacrum, S. Cyprian, Epist.</hi> 77. and <hi>Gennadius</hi> witness, who says that it was observ'd, <hi>Ʋniformiter in universo Mundo,</hi> Uniformly throughout the whole World. Thus <hi>Sparrows Rationale,</hi> on the Office of <hi>publick Baptism.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:56117:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For</hi> Oyl <hi>in</hi> Baptism; so far at least, as that there is the same Reason for <hi>that,</hi> as for the Sign of the <hi>Cross;</hi> and since Both were practis'd together by the <hi>Antient Church,</hi> so both should either be practis'd together by the <hi>Present,</hi> or both discontinued. And for the <hi>Cross</hi> out of <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether it be not fit to have some Discreet <hi>Rubrick</hi> made, to take away all <hi>Scandal</hi> from <hi>signifying</hi> the Sign of the <hi>Cross</hi> upon the <hi>Infants</hi> after <hi>Baptism,</hi> or if it shall seem more Expedient to be quite <hi>Disused,</hi> Whether this <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> should be publish'd, that in <hi>Antient Liturgies no</hi> Cross <hi>was consigned upon the Party, but where</hi> Oyle <hi>also was used;</hi> And therefore <hi>Oyl</hi> being now omitted, so may also that which was <hi>Concomitant</hi> with it, <hi>the Sign of the Cross.</hi> This Proposal I find among other <hi>Considerations</hi> on the <hi>Common-Prayer, (Consid.</hi> 20.) in the <hi>Proceeding</hi> of some worthy and Learned <hi>Divines</hi> (as they are there call'd) appointed by the <hi>Lords</hi> to meet at the Bishop of <hi>Lincolns</hi> in <hi>Westminster,</hi> touching <hi>Innovations</hi> (as they there Style them) in the Doctrine and Discipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Printed in the year 1641. The Subscribers to which <hi>Reformation</hi> of the <hi>Reformation</hi> are, the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> (i. e. <hi>Ʋsher;</hi>) Bishop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> (i. e. <hi>Williams;</hi>) Dr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> (after Bishop of <hi>Worcester;</hi>) Dr. <hi>Ward,</hi> Dr. <hi>Brownrig,</hi> (after Bishop of <hi>Exeter;</hi>) Dr. <hi>Featly,</hi> and <hi>Hacket,</hi> (after Bishop of <hi>Litchfield</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventry:</hi>) And as these <hi>Reformers</hi> were no less inclinable to the <hi>Oyl</hi> than the <hi>Cross;</hi> the one being the <hi>Antient Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant</hi> of the other; so is Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> in the <hi>Conference</hi> at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> more ready to approve the Use of the <hi>Cross</hi> out of <hi>Baptism</hi> than <hi>In</hi> it, as being in his Judgement; more <hi>undoubtedly Antient:</hi> For upon K. <hi>James</hi>'s desire, to acquaint himself with the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of the Use of the <hi>Cross;</hi> Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> confess'd it to have been ever since the <hi>Apostles Times:</hi> But the difficulty was to prove it of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56117:21"/> that <hi>Antient Ʋse</hi> in <hi>Baptism;</hi> for that at their <hi>going Abroad,</hi> or <hi>Entring into the Church,</hi> or at their <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Benedictions</hi> it was us'd by the <hi>Antients,</hi> desir'd no great Proof; but whether in <hi>Baptism, Antiquity</hi> approv'd it, was the doubt. So Dr. <hi>Raynolds,</hi> as I find it in the summe of that <hi>Conference,</hi> by <hi>Barlow</hi> Dean of <hi>Chester,</hi> in the year 1604. Thus far was he in the Right, that whatever Question there may be, whether <hi>Baptism</hi> be the same <hi>without</hi> the <hi>Cross;</hi> sure there can be none, whe- the <hi>Cross</hi> be the same <hi>without Baptism.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And though in the close of K. <hi>Edwards Liturgy,</hi> 'tis said of <hi>Crossing,</hi> as of the <hi>Tunsio Pectoris,</hi> or <hi>Knocking</hi> the <hi>Breast;</hi> that they may be <hi>used,</hi> or <hi>left,</hi> as every Mans Devotion serveth, without Blame. Yet <hi>Montague</hi> in his <hi>Appello Caesarem,</hi> denies not, that even the <hi>Primitive Christians</hi> from their frequent <hi>Veneration</hi> and <hi>Ʋse</hi> of the <hi>Cross,</hi> had the Style of <hi>Crucis Religiosi,</hi> or <hi>Worshippers</hi> of the <hi>Cross;</hi> and so far, if I mistake not, was Bishop <hi>Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue</hi> himself, a <hi>Worshipper</hi> of the <hi>Cross,</hi> as to <hi>Cross</hi> himself as duely as he repeated that Petition in the <hi>Litany, Per Crucem &amp; Passionem, By thy</hi> CROSS <hi>and Passion:</hi> Such <hi>Worshippers</hi> of the <hi>Cross</hi> were also Dr. <hi>Martin,</hi> (late Dean of <hi>Ely</hi>) and Dr. <hi>Eleazar Duncon,</hi> as they were never wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to prefix that <hi>Sign</hi> to their <hi>Writings</hi> and <hi>Papers:</hi> As appears in the <hi>Five Letters</hi> of Dr. <hi>Martin</hi> published by Dr. <hi>Watson</hi> in the year 1662. and in Dr. <hi>Eleazar Duncon</hi>'s Tract of <hi>Bowing towards the Altar:</hi> Both grounding it on that of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Thessal.</hi> 3.17. <hi>This is the Token of me in every Epistle; so I write,</hi> for their Warrant.</p>
               <p>But a more Zealous <hi>Worshipper</hi> of the <hi>Cross</hi> was Abbot <hi>Aelfrike,</hi> as appears from the following Passage. <q>They (<hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Israelites</hi>) mark'd with the <hi>Lambs Blood</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Doors</hi> and the <hi>Ʋpper-posts, Tau,</hi> that is the Sign of the <hi>Cross;</hi> and were so defended from the <hi>Angel,</hi> that kill'd the <hi>Egyptian first-born-Child, (Exod.</hi> 12.7.) And we ought to <hi>Mark</hi> our <hi>Foreheads</hi> and our <hi>Bodies</hi>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:56117:22"/> with the Token of CHRISTS Rood (or <hi>Cross</hi>) that we may be also deliver'd from Destruction; when we shall be markd both on <hi>Forehead</hi> and also in <hi>Heart,</hi> with the <hi>Blood</hi> of our <hi>Lords Suffering:</hi>
                  </q> Thus Abbot <hi>Aelfrike</hi> in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited <hi>Saxon Homily</hi> on <hi>Easter.</hi> Now as to <hi>Aelfrikes</hi> Criticism on this Passage of <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.7. and of the Letter <hi>Tau</hi>'s being the <hi>Sign</hi> of the <hi>Cross;</hi> it may appear, that the <hi>Elder Translators</hi> of the <hi>English Bible</hi> were, if not of the same Mind with him; yet not such <hi>Dissenters</hi> from him as the <hi>Present,</hi> from collating their <hi>Marginal Note</hi> on a Parallel Place, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 11.4. <hi>The Lord said unto him; go through the midst of the City, through the midst of</hi> Jerusalem; <hi>and ✚ set a</hi> Mark <hi>upon the</hi> Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads <hi>of the men that Sigh, and Cry for all the Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that be done in the midst thereof.</hi> Against which, the <hi>Older English Bibles</hi> had the Letter <hi>TAƲ</hi> in the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent,</hi> though the <hi>Later</hi> leave it out, contenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves only with the Reference to <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.7. which was in the <hi>Old.</hi> But sure, even that <hi>Reference</hi> were vain, did not both the <hi>Older Translators,</hi> and the more <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern</hi> conspire, in concluding that these <hi>Two</hi> were <hi>Parallel Places;</hi> and so, that the <hi>Mark</hi> on the <hi>Mens Foreheads</hi> in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and the <hi>Aspersion</hi> of the <hi>Lambs Blood</hi> on the <hi>two Side-posts,</hi> and the <hi>upper Door-posts</hi> of the <hi>Israelites Houses,</hi> were of the same Nature and Fashion.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sign</hi> of the <hi>Cross,</hi> as we use it, is in some sort a Means to work our Preservation from Reproach and CHRISTS <hi>Mark.</hi> Surely the <hi>Mind,</hi> which as yet has not hardned it self in <hi>Sin,</hi> is seldom provoked thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, in any gross and grievous manner, but <hi>Natures se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Suggestion objecteth</hi> against it <hi>Ignominy</hi> as a Bar: Which conceit being entred into that <hi>Palace</hi> of Mans <hi>Fancy,</hi> the <hi>Gates</hi> whereof have imprinted in them that <hi>Holy Sign,</hi> which bringeth forthwith to mind whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever CHRIST hath <hi>wrought,</hi> and <hi>We Vowed</hi> against <hi>Sin;</hi> it comes hereby to pass, that <hi>Christian Men,</hi> never want
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56117:22"/> a most <hi>Effectual,</hi> though a <hi>Silent Teacher,</hi> to avoid whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may deservedly procure <hi>Shame.</hi> Let us not think it Superfluous that <hi>Christ</hi> has his <hi>Mark</hi> apply'd unto that <hi>Part</hi> where <hi>Bashfulness</hi> appeareth; in Token that they which are <hi>Christians,</hi> should at no time be <hi>asham'd</hi> of his <hi>Ignominy:</hi> So <hi>Hooker, Ecclesiastical Policy, lib.</hi> 5. p. 162.</p>
               <p>Nor did the Use of the <hi>Cross</hi> appear so indifferent to Dr. <hi>Donne</hi> the Dean of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> upon <hi>Other Occasions</hi> besides <hi>those</hi> remembred by Dr. <hi>Raynolds</hi> above; as is evident from the following instance: <q>In the <hi>Persecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> (says he) in the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> (and therefore in the <hi>First three Centuries</hi>) 'the <hi>Martyrs</hi> which were hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Tumultuary Executions,</hi> and could not be <hi>Heard</hi> for <hi>Noise,</hi> in excusing themselves of <hi>Treason,</hi> and <hi>Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>Crimes</hi> imputed to them, to make their Cause odious, did use in <hi>Sight</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> (who might <hi>see</hi> a <hi>Gesture,</hi> though they could not <hi>hear</hi> a <hi>Protestation</hi>) to <hi>Sign</hi> themselves with the Sign of the <hi>Cross,</hi> to let them know for what <hi>Profession</hi> they <hi>Died;</hi> so that (as he concludes) the <hi>Sign</hi> of the <hi>Cross</hi> in that Use there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in that Time, was an <hi>Abridgement</hi> and a <hi>Catechism</hi> of the <hi>whole Christian Religion:</hi>
                  </q> So he, <hi>in Serm.</hi> on <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. Then which, there cannot be devis'd a more pregnant Testimony of the Import of the <hi>Cross,</hi> in the <hi>Primitive Times.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the <hi>Cross</hi> in <hi>Confirmation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Sign of the <hi>Cross</hi> was so generally received in S. <hi>Austins</hi> time, that he makes it a wonder, if any man should be ignorant of it. <hi>Quid est, quod omnes Nove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt</hi> (says he, <hi>Tractat</hi> 118. <hi>in Johan) Signum</hi> CHRISTI, <hi>nisi Crux</hi> CHRISTI? What is that which all the World takes Notice of? That <hi>Sign</hi> of CHRIST, what is it but the <hi>Cross</hi> of CHRIST? And so highly was it esteem'd by him, and the <hi>Holy-Men</hi> of <hi>that Age,</hi> that he professes, unless it be added, <hi>Sive Frontibus Credentium, sive ipsi Aquae, qua regenerantur, sive Oleo, quo Chrismate unguntur,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:56117:23"/>Unless (says he) the Sign of the <hi>Cross</hi> be used in <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism,</hi> and in <hi>Confirmation</hi> (for as he observes after, the Name of <hi>Chrisme</hi> both <hi>Councils</hi> and <hi>Fathers</hi> give to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation) Nihil eorum rite perficitur,</hi> None of them are <hi>Rightly</hi> performed:</q> That is, according to the Orders and Rites of the Church, So S. <hi>Austin.</hi> The <hi>Cross</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, upon <hi>this,</hi> or the <hi>like Consideration,</hi> is enjoyned to be used in <hi>Confirmation,</hi> in the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> set forth and allowed in <hi>Edward</hi> the VI's Reign: And I find it not at any time Revoked; but it is left (as it seems) to the <hi>Bishops</hi> Discretion to use, or not use the <hi>Cross</hi> in <hi>Confirmation;</hi> Thus <hi>Edward Boughen</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain to the Lord Bishop of <hi>Oxford,</hi> in a Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mon of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation,</hi> at the Visitation of <hi>John</hi> Lord Bishop of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> 1619. Nor stays he here, but proceeds. <q>Neither do we deduce the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of this Ceremony of the <hi>Cross,</hi> from S. <hi>Austin</hi>'s or S. <hi>Cyprians</hi> Age only, but we go higher to the Times wherein <hi>Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> flourished:</q>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> says, <hi>Caro signatur, ut &amp; Anima Muniatur (de Resur. Carnis)</hi> The Body is Signed with the <hi>Cross</hi> (in <hi>Confirmation</hi>) that the Soul may be fenced against all Temptations: And <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> (as <hi>Eusebius</hi> Notes, <hi>Hist. Eccles. l.</hi> 3.20.) observes not only the Practice of <hi>Confirmation in S. John's time,</hi> but with all this Ceremony of the <hi>Cross,</hi> whereby this <hi>Sign</hi> seems also to be <hi>Apostolique:</hi> For S. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Apostle</hi> having newly constituted a <hi>Bishop</hi> in <hi>Asia,</hi> delivered him a goodly proper <hi>Young-Man</hi> (whom he had a great liking to) to be train'd up by him in <hi>Christian Religion:</hi> The <hi>Bishop</hi> took him, and brought him up with great Care and Diligence <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and at last he <hi>Enlightned</hi> him, that is, <hi>Baptiz'd</hi> him: The <hi>Bishop</hi> having thus <hi>Baptiz'd</hi> this Young-man, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and commended to his Charge; he had such Care of him, he gave him so good and so <hi>Christian Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> that at last he added <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Seal</hi> of the Lord, meaning <hi>Confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:56117:23"/> (which was finish'd with the <hi>Sign</hi> of the <hi>Cross</hi>) which was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as a <hi>Defence</hi> or <hi>safe-guard</hi> from those Powerful Enemies, <hi>Sin</hi> and the <hi>Devil</hi> (so <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sostome</hi> uses the word) or as an <hi>Antidote</hi> against <hi>Poyson</hi> (so <hi>Physitians</hi> call it) and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the last, <hi>the most perfect Defence,</hi> he could add unto him, which was <hi>Confirmation;</hi> and therefore call'd, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Perfection</hi> of a <hi>Christian.</hi> So <hi>Boughen, Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For <hi>Prayer</hi> for the <hi>Dead.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Fulk</hi> acknowledges, that <hi>Ambrose, Chrysostome</hi> and <hi>Augustine,</hi> allowed <hi>Prayer for the Dead;</hi> and that <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, Augustine, Cyprian, Hierom,</hi> and <hi>a great many More do witness, that Prayer for the Dead, is the Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Apostles.</hi> So he, <hi>Answer to a Counterfeit Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick,</hi> pag. 44.</p>
               <p>A Treatise published by the <hi>Protestant</hi> Divines of <hi>Wittemberg</hi> in the year 1584. Intituled, <hi>Acta Theologo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Wittenbergensium,</hi> &amp;c. Affirms that the <hi>Greek</hi> Church at this day believes <hi>Invocation</hi> of <hi>Saints,</hi> and <hi>Prayer</hi> for the <hi>Dead:</hi> Which is also confirm'd by the Testimony of Sir <hi>Edwyn Sands</hi> in his <hi>Europae Speculum,</hi> p. 233. as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore noted.</p>
               <p>And for the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> let them speak for Themselves, <hi>Seimus Veteres loqui de</hi> Orationes pro Mortuis, <hi>quam Nos non prohibemus. Apol. Confes. Augustan. We know the</hi> Antients <hi>speak of</hi> Prayer for the Dead, <hi>which we forbid not.</hi> So the Apology for the <hi>Confession</hi> of <hi>Auspurg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Book, called, <hi>The Institution of a Christian Man,</hi> composed by the <hi>Bishops,</hi> and the <hi>Clergy</hi> of the <hi>Convocation,</hi> and after it was Subscribed by all their Hands, presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to K. <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. in the year 1537. for his Royal Approbation, and set forth after under the Title of, <hi>A necessary Doctrine for all sorts of People</hi> in the year 1544. with a <hi>Preface</hi> before it in the <hi>Kings</hi> Name to all his <hi>Subjects,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending it to them as a sure Directory in points of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and of <hi>Practice;</hi> in the Close concerning <hi>Prayer</hi> for the <hi>Dead,</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:56117:24"/> speaks thus, 'Since <hi>Charity</hi> dictates, and the Book of <hi>Maccabees,</hi> and also the <hi>Writings</hi> of the <hi>Antient Doctors</hi> of the Church, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it to be Wholsome and Pious, to <hi>Pray</hi> for the <hi>Dead.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause this <hi>Custom</hi> has continued in the Church from the <hi>Primitive Times,</hi> and even from those of the <hi>Apostles</hi> themselves; for that very reason is it to be supposed, that <hi>Prayers</hi> for the <hi>Dead,</hi> are Acceptable to God; and not in the least <hi>in Vain.</hi> And assuredly it is clear, that it is agreeable to <hi>Christian Charity</hi> to recommend our <hi>Neighbours living</hi> or <hi>dead</hi> in our Prayers to God, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite others, <hi>so</hi> to joyn with us in our Prayers; and to take care, that according to the <hi>Custom</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and the Opinion of the <hi>Antient Fathers,</hi> we remember our <hi>Dead Brethren</hi> in our <hi>Masses</hi> and <hi>Obits,</hi> and giving of our <hi>Doles.</hi> For such kind of Things as they are of Use and Advantage for Them, for whom they are performed, so also they express our <hi>Charity</hi> to the <hi>Dead,</hi> &amp;c. Notwithstanding their Zeal shown afterwards against the Abuses of the <hi>Papacy, Purgatory, Indulgences,</hi> and the like: Thus these <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Clergy,</hi> concerning whom Bishop <hi>Andrews</hi> in his <hi>Answer</hi> to <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is bold to say, that they were <hi>Viri summi eruditionis laude (quam late patet Orbis</hi> Christianus) <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tissimi,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Extraordinary Men, and Celebrated for the Fame of their Learning, all over the Christian World.</hi> Thus he c. 1. p. 23. of that <hi>Answer.</hi> Nor did He himself dissent from <hi>those Bishops</hi> in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular. <hi>Quod ad</hi> Orationes &amp; Oblationes pro Defunctis <hi>attinet parum est quod eis Contradici queat, negari non potest Consuetudinem eam esse Vetustam,</hi> &amp;c. So he in his Answer to <hi>Perrons</hi> Reply. As to <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Oblations</hi> for the <hi>Dead</hi> (says he) there is little to be said against them: It cannot be deny'd to be an <hi>Antient Custom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That they were in Use for the <hi>Three,</hi> or <hi>Four first Centuries,</hi> is owned by <hi>Ʋsher</hi> in his Answer to <hi>Malone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, <hi>Calvin</hi> himself could not deny but that they were <hi>most An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient,</hi> even at the same instant, when he <hi>Reformed</hi> them out of K. <hi>Edwards Liturgy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When any Party is <hi>Departed,</hi> does the <hi>Bell</hi> ring out his <hi>Knell,</hi> that Others may take notice, and thank God for his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance out of this Vale of Misery? Or, as the <hi>Antient Church</hi> used, accompany him with <hi>Intercession</hi> unto Gods <hi>Judgment Seat?</hi> Both which <hi>Tolling</hi> and <hi>Ringing</hi> out, be in many places <hi>Neglected.</hi> This is an <hi>Article,</hi> among the fore-cited <hi>Articles</hi> of Bishop <hi>Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue</hi>'s <hi>Visitation,</hi> for the Diocess of <hi>Norwich</hi> in the year 1633. <hi>Tit.</hi> 6. of <hi>Sacraments and Sacramentals.</hi> Nor is it to be forgotten that this is the same Bishop <hi>Montague,</hi> whose Memory Dr. <hi>Martin</hi> Dean of <hi>Ely</hi> professes ever to Reverence, as of a Person of as great Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Judgment and Authority, (in matter of <hi>Church-History</hi> and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56117:24"/>
                  <hi>Antiquity</hi>) as any that has Adorned the <hi>Christian Church</hi> in this our <hi>Age.</hi> Thus Dr. <hi>Martin</hi> in his 5 <hi>Letters</hi> published by Dr. <hi>Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> in the year 1662. <hi>Letter</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Such were the <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Enquiry</hi> in the <hi>Visitations</hi> of those days. And accordingly such was the <hi>Open Practice</hi> of some, even in their <hi>Pulpits,</hi> as it was pleaded for by others in the <hi>Schools.</hi> For among the <hi>Innovations</hi> (as they term them) <hi>in Doctrine,</hi> noted in the fore-cited Copy of the Proceedings of Archbishop <hi>Ʋsher,</hi> Dr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> Dr. <hi>Ward,</hi> Dr. <hi>Browning,</hi> Dr. <hi>Featly</hi> and Dr. <hi>Hacket</hi> at the Bishop of <hi>Lincolns (Williams</hi>'s) in <hi>Westminster</hi> in the year 1641. I find this remembred. Some have introduced <hi>Prayer for the Dead</hi> as Mr. <hi>Brown</hi> in his <hi>Printed Sermon,</hi> and some have coloured the Use of it with Questions in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and disputed, that <hi>Preces pro Defunctis, non supponunt Purgatorium,</hi> So they <hi>Innovat.</hi> 7. And it is very probable they took up this Cavil from the Libeller <hi>Burton,</hi> who in his <hi>two Sermons</hi> and <hi>Apology</hi> 2636. raises the same Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint against <hi>Brown</hi> on the same score. To whom Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> returns this in his Defence. <hi>Browns Prayer</hi> before his <hi>Sermon</hi> if you are agrieved at, you may find the very Clause <hi>Verbatim</hi> in K. <hi>Edwards first Liturgy, Anno</hi> 1549. which in that very <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> wherein the <hi>Second</hi> was Confirmed, is said to be <hi>a very Godly Order, agreeable to the Word of God, and the Primitive Church.</hi> Thus <hi>Heylin,</hi> in his Answer to <hi>Burton, cap.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>And that these <hi>Prayers for the Dead</hi> had preserved their Place and Esteem in the <hi>present Liturgy,</hi> is the Wish of <hi>Forbes</hi> Bishop of <hi>Edenburgh;</hi> nor can he forbear falling into a just and free Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stulation with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for Dissenting from the <hi>Antient Church,</hi> in her leaving them out; for upon Occasion of remembring those <hi>Formes</hi> in the <hi>Communion-Office,</hi> as well as in that of the <hi>Burial</hi> of the <hi>Dead</hi> in K. <hi>Edward</hi>'s <hi>Liturgy,</hi> he has these words, <hi>Hasce Preces</hi> Antiquissimas <hi>&amp;</hi> Piissimas, Buceri, <hi>alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum{que} monitu &amp; Concilio, postea</hi> Praesules Ecclesiae Anglicanae <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punxere, aut in Aliam, nescio quam Formam, hodiernam Novitatem redolentem convertere:</hi> Isaacus Casaubonus <hi>in Respon. ad Epist. Card.</hi> Petronii, <hi>nomine Serenissimae Su.</hi> Britanniae <hi>scripta Affirmat hunc Ritum</hi> Orandi <hi>pro</hi> Mortuis Ecclesiam Anglicanam, <hi>&amp; si non damnet in</hi> Primis Seculis, <hi>hodie tamen sibi non putare retinendum,</hi> &amp;c. p. 54. And then proceeds as follows, <hi>Sed utinam</hi> Ecclesia Anglica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, <hi>quae singularem certe alioqui meretur Laudem; ob magnam multis aliis in Rebus, &amp; si forte non paris Momenti, Moderationem adhibitam,</hi> Universalis Ecclesiae antiquissimae Consuetudini <hi>hoc in negotio, ut &amp; in</hi> aliis Nonnullis, <hi>sese potius Conformaret, sed, quam ob Errores &amp; Abusus, qui paulatim irrepserant postea, ingenti cum aliorum fere</hi> Omnium Christianorum Scandalo <hi>simpliciter rejecisset, &amp; penitus
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56117:25"/> sustulisset. Forbesii Considerationes Pacificae &amp; Modestae, Consid. de Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorio part.</hi> 2. c. 3. §. 19. <q>These <hi>Primitive</hi> and <hi>Devout Prayers</hi> (says he, speaking of those <hi>Formes</hi> for the <hi>Dead</hi>) 'the <hi>Bishops</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> afterwards, at the Instigation and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of <hi>Bucer</hi> and <hi>Others,</hi> rased out, or gave them I know not what Turn, more savouring of <hi>Modern Novelty. Isaac Causau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> (as he goes on) in an <hi>Answer</hi> of his, in the Name of the K. of <hi>Great Britain</hi> made to Cardinal <hi>Perrons Letter,</hi> says, That the Church of <hi>England,</hi> although she condemns not the Practice of <hi>Prayer for the Dead</hi> in the <hi>First Centuries,</hi> (so early then it was in Use) yet she thinks it not Expedient for her to retain that Usage at this day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 54, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> (a fair Confession of her Renouncing the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> after all her boasted Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions to it:) With which <hi>Answer</hi> the <hi>Bishop</hi> not at all satisfied, proceeds as follows. <q>But it were to be wished that the Church of <hi>England,</hi> (says he) which otherwise merits no small Praise for her great Moderation shown in many other Things, and those perhaps not of the same Moment; had on <hi>this Occasion</hi> and <hi>some Others</hi> Conformed to the most <hi>Antient Practice</hi> of the <hi>Ʋni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal Church,</hi> rather than for some <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Abuses</hi> that crept in after by degrees, to the great Scandal of almost all other <hi>Christians;</hi> absolutely to have Renounced, and entirely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved this <hi>Ʋsage.</hi>
                  </q> So Bishop <hi>Forbes,</hi> the first Bishop of <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> who held that esteem with K. <hi>Charles</hi> the I. That, upon the Archbishop of S. <hi>Andrews</hi> enquiry at the <hi>King</hi>'s first Erection of <hi>Edenburgh</hi> into an <hi>Episcopal See,</hi> Whom his <hi>Majesty</hi> designed for that <hi>Promotion: Who</hi> (says his Royal Master freely) <hi>but For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes? Worthy</hi> (as you your self well know) <hi>to fill a greater Chair.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To pass nearer yet to our Times. In the Copy of her <hi>Royal Highness,</hi> the late Dutchess of <hi>York</hi>'s Motives, set forth by <hi>Royal Authority,</hi> in the year 1686. We are assured upon the Word of that Excellent <hi>Princess:</hi>
                  <q>That having some Speech with <hi>Two</hi> of the <hi>best Bishops</hi> we had in <hi>England,</hi> (that is <hi>Sheldon</hi> A. B. of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> and <hi>Blandford</hi> B. of <hi>Worcester,</hi> as the Margent acquaints us) '<hi>They both</hi> told her, there were <hi>Many Things</hi> in the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> which (it were <hi>very much</hi> to be <hi>Wished,</hi> they are their own Words) <hi>We</hi> had <hi>kept;</hi> as <hi>Confession,</hi> which was no doubt, <hi>Commanded by God:</hi> That <hi>Praying for the Dead,</hi> was one of the <hi>Antient Things</hi> in <hi>Christianity.</hi> Nor do they stay here, but add, That for their Parts, they <hi>did</hi> it <hi>Daily,</hi> though, they would <hi>not own it.</hi>
                  </q> From which frank Confession it appears, that those <hi>two Prelates</hi> were good Invisible <hi>Catholicks</hi> at the same time in their <hi>Closets,</hi> and good Visible <hi>Protestants,</hi> in their <hi>Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:56117:25"/>
               <p>But what was the Concealed Practice of these <hi>Prelates</hi> in Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, seems to have been the Open and Avowed Practice or Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Others</hi> of the <hi>same Communion,</hi> who have not stuck to make as Solemn Mourn and Lamentation for these <hi>lost Devotions,</hi> as for their <hi>lost Friends.</hi> Such was the above-named Bishop <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes,</hi> to whom we may add the Learned <hi>Herbert Thorndike,</hi> late Prebend of <hi>Westminster,</hi> who in his last <hi>Manuscript-Paper,</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before his Death under his own Hand, was bold to Note and Bewail it as <hi>a Defect in the Reformation, that it wanted Prayers for the Dead:</hi> But what the <hi>Reformation wanted,</hi> he took Care to <hi>supply</hi> for his own <hi>Particular,</hi> by leaving this <hi>Epitaph</hi> behind him, when he was Buried in <hi>Westminster,</hi> of which Church he was Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bend. <hi>Hic jacet</hi> Herbertus Thorndike, <hi>quondam hujus Ecclesiae Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendarius. Qui Vivus, veram Rationem &amp; Modum Reformandae Ecclesiae, Precibus Studiis{que} prosequibatur. Tu Lector</hi> Requiem ei in CHRISTO, <hi>&amp; beatam Resurrectionem precare. Here lyes</hi> Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Thorndike, <hi>once Prebend of this Church: Who Living, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued the true Way and Method of</hi> Reforming the Church <hi>by his Prayers and Studies. Thou Reader Pray for his</hi> Requiem <hi>in</hi> CHRIST, <hi>and Happy Resurrection.</hi> So equal a <hi>Reconciler</hi> was he betwixt the <hi>Catholicks</hi> and <hi>Protestants,</hi> that <hi>Erasmus</hi>-like, he hung between both; for if the <hi>Protestants</hi> had him <hi>Living,</hi> he gave himself <hi>Dead</hi> to the <hi>Catholicks:</hi> And as his <hi>Epitaph</hi> begins (like <hi>Himself</hi>) with <hi>Reforming of the Church;</hi> so it ends (like <hi>Himself</hi>) with <hi>Reforming of the Reformation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>More briefly and plainly yet Dr. <hi>Barrow</hi> late Bishop of S <hi>Asaph,</hi> (who could not be frighted from this practice, though he died during the Heat of the late <hi>Plot) Ora, pro Anima Mea.</hi> And though both their <hi>Epitaphs</hi> met with the like Fate, to be <hi>Buried</hi> together with their <hi>Authors;</hi> yet may it seem a Work of some Piety to give them that <hi>Resurrection,</hi> which they so earnestly wished for <hi>Themselves.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For <hi>Communions</hi> (or <hi>Masses</hi>) for the <hi>Dead.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A <hi>Latin Copy</hi> of the <hi>Service-Book</hi> Printed 2 <hi>Eliz.</hi> has in it an <hi>Office</hi> for <hi>Communions</hi> at <hi>Burials (Celebratio Caenae Domini in Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ibus,</hi> &amp;c.) And <hi>Offertories</hi> at <hi>Burials</hi> did lest to be Frequent (if they were <hi>Considerable Funerals</hi>) to the middle of K. <hi>James</hi> his Reign. Nor is the fore-mentioned <hi>Communion Office</hi> to be pass'd over, as a Celebration that stole out from a Private Hand without Authority. For that <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> was done into <hi>Latine</hi> by Command, and Authorized by the Great Seal of Q. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> So, <hi>Coal from the Altar,</hi> p. 23. Esteemed to be the work of <hi>Walter Haddon;</hi> and Recommended by the Queen to all the Colledges in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:56117:26"/>
                  <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> the Colledges of <hi>Winchester</hi> and <hi>Eaton,</hi> &amp;c. to be received into Use; for so run her <hi>Letters Patents. Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam Intelligimus Collegia utrius{que} Academiae, Collegium item Novum prope</hi> Wintoniam <hi>&amp;</hi> Aetonenses, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Q. <hi>Letters Patents</hi> 6 <hi>April. Eliz.</hi> 2. And for what is Peculiar in the <hi>Obits</hi> and <hi>Exequies,</hi> and runs Counter to the <hi>Statute,</hi> it is warranted by the <hi>Queens</hi> special <hi>Non Obstante. Peculiaria quaedam in Funebribus &amp; Exequiis decan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanda, quae Statuto non obstante,</hi> &amp;c. say the same <hi>Letters Patents.</hi> Thus <hi>Holy Table, Name and Thing. pag.</hi> 56, 57. At Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> first coming to the Crown, a <hi>Proclamation</hi> was set forth, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any man to alter any <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> but according to the <hi>Rites</hi> of her own <hi>Chappel;</hi> which were indeed the entire <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of the <hi>Mass,</hi> but that the <hi>Lords Supper, Creed</hi> &amp; <hi>Litany</hi> was in <hi>English,</hi> as was usual in her <hi>Fathers</hi> time, <hi>Camdens Eliz.</hi> p. 23. <hi>Stow</hi> p. 614. <hi>Litany with Suffrages,</hi> Printed 16 of <hi>June</hi> 1544. As therefore that Wise <hi>Princess</hi> made shift for a time with her <hi>Sisters Seal,</hi> so did she with <hi>Her Ceremonies,</hi> but forsook them <hi>Both</hi> as soon as she could otherwise be provided.<note place="margin">She had a <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifix</hi> on her <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar</hi> in her <hi>Chappel.</hi> So <hi>Thuanus Hist.</hi> l. 13. p. 670.</note> So <hi>Holy Table, Name and Thing,</hi> pag. 34, 35. leaving the <hi>Colledges</hi> at more Liberty in their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>Obits</hi> and <hi>Exequies,</hi> as also in their <hi>Latine Service,</hi> and the <hi>Monkery</hi> of their <hi>Fellowes;</hi> by it all which should seem, that the <hi>Colledges</hi> in those days appear'd like the Remainder of the <hi>Latine</hi> Church, which stood out from the rest of their Fellows, as being not yet come over to the <hi>Reformation;</hi> in the same nature as the <hi>Kentish</hi> Men refused to Bow to the <hi>Conquerors</hi> Sword, until he had confirm'd to them their <hi>Antient Priviledges.</hi> For after all the Noise of the <hi>Queens</hi> Act of <hi>Ʋniformity,</hi> so distant was the Face of Worship in the <hi>Collegiate Churches</hi> of those Days, from that in the <hi>other Churches,</hi> as the Distance between the present <hi>Cathedral</hi> and <hi>Parochial Churches</hi> appears not greater; whose <hi>Modes</hi> are yet so different, as notwithstanding the <hi>late Kings</hi> like boasted <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Ʋniformity;</hi> the <hi>Dissenters</hi> who are at fierce War with the <hi>One,</hi> want but a little of Closing with the <hi>Other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude, It appears upon a Review of the Premises, that the <hi>Exiled Cavaliers</hi> and <hi>Sequestred Clergy,</hi> upon the <hi>late Kings</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn did not more earnestly-long for the Restoration of the <hi>New Liturgy,</hi> nor the <hi>Dissenters</hi> and <hi>Silenced Non-conformists,</hi> after the <hi>Bartholomew-Tide</hi> Suspencion thirst for <hi>No Liturgy</hi> more zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously, than the fore-named <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Churchmen</hi> have renewed their <hi>Desires</hi> for the <hi>Old-Liturgy:</hi> Wishing no less passionately for the <hi>Antient Liturgy</hi> of the <hi>Primitive Reformation,</hi> than the Church of <hi>England</hi> does with one Voice in the <hi>Commination-Office</hi> on <hi>Ash-Wednesdays,</hi> cry out for the <hi>Antient Discipline</hi> of the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>